Talking Points for Secretary's Call to North Korea Detainee's Family
1
Cheryl Mills <cheryLmill5
Friday, March 20, 2009 6:02 AM
'Abedin, Huma'; 'Coleman, Claire L'
Talking Points for Call with Sen Feinstein and Greg Craig
HRC talking points on Goodwin - Craig.doc; HRC talking points on Goodwin -
Feinstein.doc
Attached are two sets of talking points I will have Claire print for you today for two call on behalf of
Goodwin's candidacy for the Ninth Circuit.
The first set is for Sen Feinstein, which stresses Goodwin's moderate judgment — she apparently needs
reassurance that Goodwin is not too liberal.
The other set is for Greg Craig, which stresses Goodwin's progressive credentials as he likely will find that
more appealing.
cdm
I've printed these and will give a copy to the Secretary and also to Huma.
Claire
Story below is as good and straightforward as they come. It's a reflection of one of the best new-old partnerships I've
seen in the bulding: Caroline Adler and PA's two in-house new media guys, Luke Forgerson & Dan Schaub..Refelcting
your prioritization, she - along with Katie Dowd, have helped these guys unleash the full potential of this new kind of
communications.
Selling it to Matt was the easy part. Those guys are doing all the real work. And anecdotally, they're seeing great
success already - with a lot more to come.
E-diplomacy? Hillary Clinton Embraces New Media By MATTHEW LEE AP Sat, Mar 21, 2009
WASHINGTON (AP) — Her videos aren't quite viral yet and she's not tweeting, but Secretary of State Hillary Rodham
Clinton is embracing new media, using the Web to promote the agency and her role as the nation's top envoy.
In less than three months, Clinton's State Department has embarked on a digital diplomacy drive aimed at spreading the
word about American foreign policy and restoring Washington's image. Part of a broader Internet outreach by President
Barack Obama's administration, Clinton's Web efforts already have outpaced those of her predecessors.
Since taking over at Foggy Bottom, Clinton's team has built on e-diplomacy innovations developed during George W.
Bush's presidency:
- They have revamped the department's Web site (http://www.state.gov) and the Dipnote blog (http://blogs.state.gov
and http://twitter.com/dipnote) with a fresh array of features, graphics and colorful posts.
- Users can track her foreign travel on an interactive map (http://www.state.gov/secretary/trvI/map/?trip_id5)
- They can keep up virtually with her every move through Facebook, Twitter, Flickr and YouTube
(http://www.youtube.com/user/statevideo).
- They can pose questions through an "ask-the-secretary" column
(http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/ask/secretary/117297.htm) that recently was revised to "text the secretary."
(http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/ask/secretary/120236.htm)
"New media is critical in this new era of diplomacy, where smart power and expanded dialogues are essential to
achieving our foreign policy goals," said Cheryl Mills, Clinton's longtime confidante and chief of staff.
Even for a government Web site, early indications show a surge in interest, according to internal State Department
statistics provided to The Associated Press.
Daily views of the Dipnote have doubled from 10,000 a year ago to 20,000 today, with 700 subscribers to its RSS feed,
twice as many as in March 2008. The number of followers of the department on Twitter has tripled since Jan. 20, when
Obama took office, while the department's Facebook friends have increased by 2 1/2 times in the same period.
8
"What they are bringing in is more willingness to experiment," said Peter Daou, who was Clinton's Web guru during her
2008 presidential run. "They are starting to push the envelope."
What remains unclear, though, is whether the spike in interest reflects the revamped Web site or the public's fascination
with Clinton's latest career shift.
"The personality behind it can't be dismissed," said Daou, who now blogs on human rights and other issues for U.N.
Dispatch (http://www.undispatch.com).
Like Obama, Clinton carries a Blackberry, but she is not allowed to use it on the department's secure seventh floor
where her office is. Aides say she takes an active role in answering questions from the Web, responding to bloggers and
pushing her agency's new media agenda.
"The United States Government is behind nearly everybody, except in certain discrete areas, in terms of technology,"
she told department employees at a town hall meeting in February. "We are, in my view, wasting time, wasting money,
wasting opportunities, because we are not prepared to communicate effectively with what is out there in the business
world and the private world."
Clinton was quick to embrace new media at the start of her presidential campaign. She announced her entry into the
race in February 2007 on the Web and followed with regular Internet chats and Internet fundraising appeals.
Nonetheless, Clinton was surpassed by the Obama campaign's mastery of the Internet and social networking sites.
Obama used the Web to raise record donations and identify and orchestrate an army of volunteers.
Clinton was first lady when the first White House Web site debuted in 1994. It was a bare-bones operation compared
with what is available now. Three years later, the State Department went online during Secretary of State Madeleine
Albright's tenure.
But it wasn't until 2007, under Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice's spokesman, Sean McCormack, that the
department's public affairs shop began exploring new media in earnest. McCormack started the Dipnote blog, which
some foreign service veterans predicted would fail, given the private and stuffy nature of diplomacy.
The site endured under Rice. Clinton has retooled Dipnote with a Twitter feed and a broader range of posts from
diplomats.
It's more than just window dressing. This past week, diplomats used Twitter to "tweet" down false rumors they feared
might lead to a siege on the U.S. Embassy in Madagascar.
On her first two foreign trips, to Asia and then the Middle East and Europe, local bloggers were "embedded" with the
traveling press corps, broadening the audience for Clinton's official meetings and public appearances, which often
produce more personal than policy questions.
On her question site, Clinton has responded to a varied questions, from "Should the U.S. engage in direct dialogue with
Hamas?" to "How did you like meeting the Japanese students?"
By the end of Clinton's trip to the Mideast, her "text the secretary" feature had received nearly 2,000 text messages. On
both trips, Clinton also participated in Webcasts. One in Beijing on climate change generated more than 10.2 million
page views, more than 50,000 comments and 7,000 questions, according to the statistics.
Clinton's staff say they plan to venture further into the realm of social networking, an animated online world called
Second Life, and cell phone technology. The department hopes to follow through on a Bush administration organized
9
project that brought together Facebook, Google, Howcast, YouTube, AT&T, MTV, Columbia Law School, Access360Media
and Gen-Next for an Alliance of Youth Movements summit.
It also wants to expand on X-Life, a mobile phone game launched in February that is aimed at helping youth in the
Middle East learn English and teaching them about American history, culture and values.
Copyright © 2009 The Associated Press. All rights reserved.
10
Your message was delivered to the recipient.
Yes I am working with the computer folks to find the best way -- will have a new version to show you soon.
Just e-mailed me to say he is at his hotel in San Francisco. If you're available to talk tonight, he's on his cell. Otherwise, I
told him, we'll connect the two of you tomorrow.
Lauren
Lauren Jiloty
Special Assistant to
Secretary Hillary Rodham Clinton
16
We have just received an action memo seeking a timely decision on State's position on a trade dispute with
Mexico. EEB and WHA have competing recommendations.
First, some background. Mexico requested a WTO panel to resolve its tuna/dolphin dispute with the United
States U.S. measures prohibit Mexican tuna from being labeled "dolphin safe" even though the tuna is
harvested in accordance with the Agreement on the International Dolphin Conservation Program. However,
dolphin population recovery has not occurred as rapidly as expected under that Program. Despite the measures,
Mexico exported about $18 million worth of tuna to the United States in 2007.
17
18
Sullivan, Jacob J <SullivanJJ©state.gov>
Monday, March 23, 2009 10:12 PM
RE: Mexico tuna/dolphin case
I have already pinged WHA to get their recommendation on how to approach this tomorrow. I would guess a call to Kirk
and follow-up with the NSC. We will have a game plan first thing in the am.
Yes will do.
FYI - email to me and Jake from Lourdes - the woman we intend to steal I believe ...
Cdm
FYI
FYI
FYI
HRC:
I asked Anne-Marie to write up a discussion we had regarding
See below - and let me know if any issues; otherwise -- I am going to set this up.
cdm
Love it.
cdm
fvi
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Wednesday, March 25, 2009 6:39 PM
FW: Obama's Personnel Problem
Cheryl Mills <cheryl.mill
Thursday, March 26, 2009 7:04 AM
FW:
B6
we still need to decide what to do for them
Will do
Jiloty, Lauren C <JilotyLC©state.gov>
Thursday, March 26, 2009 11:04 AM
.
FYI
Cheryl Mills
Thursday, March 26, 2009 11:25 AM
Sullivan, Jacob J
FW: Mexico
B6
If this is an important message we can highlight in her speech today. I'll consult here, Cheryl, if you can follow up with
Jose.
cheryl.mills
Thursday, March 26, 2009 12:21 PM
H; Jake Sullivan
Re: Mexico
B6
See below
###
5
FYI
Neera Tanden
Saturday, March 28, 2009 12:37 AM
Re:
B6
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Saturday, March 28, 2009 12:17 PM
Fw: A little positive reinforcement to pass on to the S
See below
Attached is a draft of your Mexico trip report to POTUS. I'm also sending it by fax. I look forward to incorporating your
edits.
1Q
Message sent to north thru ny. No word back
Sounds good.
Will do
OBO is a critical element in the. Department's infrastructure arsenal as it rents, maintains,
and/or constructs all of the Department's real estate assets overseas, valued in the billions of
dollars.
From 2001 through 2007 it went through a very difficult time
Since then OBO has been run well,
and its basic morale restored, by a retired Foreign Service: Officer who had previously been its
Deputy Director and who I brought out of retirement temporarily.
Secretary Clinton, Hi,
Thank you! I am available to talk any time. I would also be happy to come to Washington (or wherever)
to discuss this in person at your convenience.
\ so after 1:30 pm tomorrow would be
safest. My cell is
Yrs, Jackie
On Sun, Mar 29, 2009 at 2:30 PM, H <hdr22@c1intonemai1.com> wrote:
Jackie—I'd like to talk to you about your choices. Michelle Fluornoy, new Undersecretary at DOD, asked me
about young women who could work w her in planning and whom she could mentor. And, of course, I thought
of you!
When would be good times for me to call you? Best, H
Jacqueline Newmyer
President, Long Term Strategy Group
12 Eliot St., Cambridge, MA 02138
617-661-1620 (ph)
617-661-1626 (fax)
www.ltstrategy.com
ps I am also looking forward to telling you about my meeting with Anne-Marie on Thursday. Thank you very
much for that as well!
On Sun, Mar 29, 2009 at 3:44 PM, Jackie Newmyer wrote:
Secretary Clinton, Hi,
Thank you! I am available to talk any time. I would also be happy to come to Washington (or wherever)
to discuss this in person at your convenience.
\ so after 1:30 pm tomorrow would be
safest. My cell is
Yrs, Jackie
On Sun, Mar 29, 2009 at 2:30 PM, H <hdr22@clintonemai1.com> wrote:
Jackie--I'd like to talk to you about your choices. Michelle Fluornoy, new Undersecretary at DOD, asked me
about young women who could work w her in planning and whom she could mentor. And, of course, I
thought of you!
When would be good times for me to call you? Best, H
Jacqueline Newmyer
President, Long Term Strategy Group
12 Eliot St., Cambridge, MA 02138
617-661-1620 (ph)
617-661-1626 (fax)
www.ltstrategy.com
Jacqueline Newmyer
President, Long Term Strategy Group
12 Eliot St., Cambridge, MA 02138
617-661:1620 (ph)
617-661-1626 (fax)
www.ltstrategy.com
Your message was delivered to the recipient.
PVerveer
B6
Sunday, March 29, 2009 7:57 PM
Re: Thank you for meeting
I'll be there if the Republicans don't try to stop me!
In a message dated 3/29/2009 7:47:13 P.M. Eastern Daylight Time, hdr22@clintonemail.com writes:
Thanks, Melanne, and congrats on your hearing. I hope you're at work when I get back next week! I'll see what I
can do to focus on Zohra's concerns. Best, H
Your message was delivered to the recipient.
B6
Read this - it says todd stern sent chills up someone's spin (in a good way)!
Fyi
Sent via BlackBerry by AT&T
Secretary Clinton,
Pending our conversation, I thought I owed Anne-Marie a thank you and follow up message because we had a
terrific chat on Thursday,
bringing to bear the best extra-governmental academic expertise
through the Long Term Strategy Group so I just sent a proposal memo (attached and pasted in
below). Thank you again for recommending me and for all of your advice.
I am most eager to help however I can and look forward to hearing your thoughts.
All best. Jackie
Memorandum
To: Department of State
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Monday, March 30, 2009 3:53 PM
FW: DPRK/CHINA: AMCIT BORDER DETENTIONS UPDATE #11
FYI
— Reason: 1.4(B), 1.4(D) — Declassify on: 03/29/2034
Jake:
Can you getline travelling to get you high side materials for hrc.
We also need a quote for inclusion from her.
Cdm
Fyi
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Tuesday, March 31, 2009 6:14 AM
H; Mills, Cheryl D; Sullivan, Jacobi
Re: UNHRC
We are tracking this down.
See below.
cdm
• Intervention excerpt, as delivered:
"We must also support efforts by the Government of Afghanistan to separate the extremists of al-Qaida and the Taliban
from those who joined their ranks not out of conviction, but out of desperation. This is, in fact, the case for a majority of
those fighting with the Taliban. They should be offered an honorable form of reconciliation and reintegration into a
peaceful society if they are willing to abandon violence, break with al-Qaida, and support the constitution."
• CNN excerpt:
QUESTION: And on this reconciliation, bringing members of the Taliban or al-Qaida
SECRETARY CLINTON: Only the Taliban, we never said al-Qaida. We never said al-Qaida. We have no interest in any
kind of reconciliation or any rapprochement by anyone with al-Qaida.
QUESTION: I'm glad you clarified that
40
