B6
Thursday, March 3, 2011 9:45 PM
H: Latest How Syria is aiding Qaddafi and more... Sid
hrc memo syria aiding libya 030311.docx; hrc memo syria aiding libya 030311.docx
March 3, 2011
For: Hillary
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Friday, March 11, 2011 1:36 PM
Huma Abedin
Fw: H: Latest: How Syria is aiding Qaddafi and more... Sid
hrc memo syria aiding libya 030311.docx
Pis print.
H <hrod17@clintonemail.corn>
Friday, March 11, 2011 1:36 PM
Huma Abedin
Fw: H: Latest: How Syria is aiding Qaddafi and more... Sid
hrc memo Syria aiding libya 030311.docx
Pis print.
Fyi
B6
— —
Anne-Marie Slaughter
Sunday, March 13, 2011 9:39 PM
Jacob Mills, Cheryl D; Reinesp@stategov; Abedin, Hurtle
piece on libya nfz that will appear on NYT op-ed page tomorrow
B6
wanted to make sure you had a heads up. AM
Anne-Marie Slaughter is a professor of politics and international affairs at Princeton.
By Anne-Marie Slaughter
PRESIDENT Obama says the noose is tightening around Col. Muammar al-Qaddafi. In fact, it is
tightening around the Libyan rebels, as Colonel Qaddafi makes the most of the world's dithering and
steadily retakes rebel-held tow.ns, The United States and Europe are temporizing on a no-flight zone
while the Organization of the Islamic Conference, the Gulf Cooperation Council and now the Arab
League have all called on the United Nations Security Council to authorize one. Opponents of a no-
flight zone have put forth five main arguments, none of which, on closer examination, hold up.
It's not in our interest. Gen. Wesley K. Clark argues that "Libya doesn't sell much oil to the United
States" and that while Americans "want to support democratic movements in the region," they are
already doing that in Iraq and Afghanistan. Framing this issue in terms of oil is exactly what Arab
populations and indeed much of the world expect, which is why they are so cynical about our
professions of support for democracy and human rights. Now we have a chance to support a new
beginning in the Muslim world — a new beginning of accountable governments that can provide
services and opportunities for their citizens in ways that could dramatically decrease support for
terrorist groups and violent extremism. It's hard to imagine something more in our strategic interest.
It will be counter-productive. Many thoughtful commentators, including Al Jazeera's director
general, Wadah Khanfar, argue that what is most important about the Arab spring is that it is coming
from Arabs themselves. From this perspective, Western military intervention will play right into
Qaddati's hands, allowing him to broadcast pictures of Western bombs falling on Arab civilians. But
these arguments, while important, must be weighed against the appeals of of Libyan opposition
fighters asking for international help, and now, astonishingly, against support for a no-flight zone by
some of the same governments that have kept their populations quiescent by holding up the specter of
foreign intervention. Assuming that a no-flight zone can be imposed by an international coalition that
includes Arab states, we have an opportunity to establish a new narrative of Western support for Arab
democrats.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739568
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045012
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739568
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
It won't work. The United States ambassador to NATO, Ivo H. Daaider, argues that stopping
Colonel Qaddafi's air force will not be decisive; he will continue to inflict damage with tanks and
helicopters, bombing oil refineries and depots on his way to retaking key towns. But the potential
effect of a no-flight zone must also be assessed in terms of Colonel Qaddafi's own calculations about
his future. Richard Downie of the Center for Strategic and International Studies argues that although
Colonel Qaddafi cultivates a mad-dictator image, he has been a canny survivor and political
manipulator for 40 years. He is aware of debates with regard to a no-flight zone and is timing his
military campaign accordingly; he is also capable of using his air force just enough to gain strategic
advantage, but not enough to trigger a no-flight zone. If the international community lines up against
him and is willing to crater his runways and take out his antiaircraft weapons, he might well renew his
offer of a negotiated departure.
If it does work, we don't know what we will get. Revolutions are almost always followed by internal
divisions among the revolutionaries. We should not expect a rosy, Jeffersonian Libya. But the choice
is between uncertainty and the certainty that if Colonel Qaddafi wins, regimes acrosS the region will
conclude that force is the livay to answer protests. And when Colonel Qaddafi massacres the
opposition, young protesters across the Middle East will conclude that when we were asked to support
their cause with more than words, we blinked. Americans in turn will read the words of Mr. Obama's
June 2009 speech in Cairo., with its lofty promises to stand for universal human rights, and cringe.
Let's arm the rebels instead. Some commentators who agree with the analysis above say we could
'better accomplish our goals by providing intelligence and arms to the opposition. That would, of
course, be much easier for us. It undoubtedly appeals to Mn Obama as a neat compromise between
the desire to help the protesters and the desire not to overrule his defense secretary's reluctance to
participate in a no-flight zone. But we would be providing arms not to a disciplined military, but to
ragged groups of brave volunteers who barely know how to use the weapons they have. They need
action that will change the situation on. the ground for Colonel Qaddafi, as well as his the calculations.
Moreover, by the time arms and intelligence could take effect, it is quite likely that Colonel Qaddafi
will have retaken or at least besieged .Benghazi, the opposition stronghold.
The United States should immediately ask the Security Council to authorize a no-flight zOne and
make clear to Russia and China that if they block the resolution, the blood of the Libyan opposition
will be on their hands. We should push them at least to abstain and bring the issue to a vote as soon as
possible. If we get a resolution, we should work with the Arab League to quickly assemble an
international coalition to impose the no-flight zone. If the Security Council fails toact, then we should
recognize the opposition Interim National Council as the legitimate Libyan government, as France has
done, and work with the Arab League to give the council any assistance it requests:
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739568
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045013
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739568
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
Any use of force must be carefully and fully debated, but that debate has now been had. Ifs been
raging for a week, during which almost every Arab country has come on board calling for a no-flight
zone and Colonel Qaddafi has retaken two key cities and is moving toward three more. It is time to
act. $
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739568
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-5CB0045014
B5
See note below
B6
Sunday, March 27, 201i 9:05 PM
H: Lots of new intel; possible Libyan collapse. Sid
hic memo lots of new Intel; possible imminent collapse 032711.docx; hrc memo lots of
new intel; possible imminent collapse 032711.docx
March 27. 2011
For: Hillary
From Sid
Re: Lots of new Intel; Libyan army possibly on verge of collapse
Latest:
During the evening of March 27, 2011, individuals with direct access to the military committee of the National
Libyan Council (NLC) stated in confidence that while the rebel forces continue to have organization and
communications problems, their morale has improved drastically, and they believe the Libyan Army is on the
verge of collapse. Under attack from allied Air and Naval forces, the Libyan Army troops have begun to desert
to the rebel side in increasing numbers. The rebels are making an effort togeet these troops as fellow Libyans,
in an effort to encourage additional defections.
(Source Comment: Speaking in strict confidence, one rebel commander stated that his troops continue to
summarily execute all foreign mercenaries captured in the fighting. At the same time Colonel Khalifa Haftzu•
has reportedly joined the rebel command structure, in an effort to help organization the rebel forces. Haftar was
the commander of the Libyan National Army ([NA), a 1500 man force of anti-Qaddafi troops based in
N'djamena, Chad, until current President Idryss Debi overthrew Chadian President Hussein Habre in the fall of
1990, with the assistance of Libyan and French troops. Haftar and his troops lied to a cotaatry in central Africa
and many, including Haftar, later settled in the United States.)
An extremely sensitive source added that the rebels are receiving direct assistance and training from a small
number of Egyptian Special Forces units, while French and British Special Operations troops are working out of
bases in Egypt, along the Libyan border. These troops are overseeing the transfer of weapons and supplies to
the rebels.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739594
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045018
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739594
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
(Source Comment: The rebels are moving back into 'areas that they lost in mid- March fighting, and using the
allied air cover, they are confident they can move into the Tripoli district in a matter of days. One rebel source
reported that they had reliable intelligence that people were evacuating Qaddafi's hometown, Sirte, anticipating
its capture by the rebels. Sirte is located mid-way between Tripoli and Benghazi; its loss will be a
psychological blow for Qaddall.)
Separately, a sensitive European source stated in strict confidence that French military commanders anticipate a
complete collapse of the Libyan military command and control structure in the next week. These officers, who
have experience with the Libyan Army during its invasion of Chad in the late 1980s stated that the Libyan
troops did not perform well under concentrated fire from troops armed with modern weapons.
This source also noted that information from Tripoli has become increasingly difficult to obtain, but there are
reports of deaths among some Qaddafi's senior security officials, including Mansour Daw, and that the Libyan
leader himself may have experienced a health problem. Unfortunately, the European Intelligence services have
been unable to confirm or discredit these reports. This situation has become increasingly frustrating for French
President Nicolas Sarkozy, who, according to knowledgeable individuals, is pressing to have France emerge
from this crisis as the principal foreign ally of any new government that takes power.
Sarkozy is also concerned about continuing reports that radical/terrorist groups such as the Libyan Fighting
Groups and Al Qa'ida in the Islamic Maghreb (AQIM) are infiltrating the NLC. and its military command.
Accordingly, he asked sociologist who has long established ties to Israel, Syria, and other B6
nations in the Middle East, to use his contacts to determine the level of influence AQIM and other terrorist
groups have inside of the NLC. Sarkozy also asked for reports setting out a clear picture of the role of the
Muslim Brotherhood in the rebel leadership.
These sources note that French diplomats and intelligence officers in Egypt are in contact with the following
rebel figures in Benghazi:
MESMAR1Nouri (Qaddafi's former head of protocol, who along with Mousa Kousa was considered the Libyan
leaders most loyal follower. Noun currently lives in France;
.Gehan (GI-LEI-LAND Abdallah (colonel);
CHARRA.NT Faraj,
BOUKHRIS Fathi,
General Abdelfateh Younis (commander of the rebel forces)
(Source Comment: Senior European security officials caution that AQIM is watching developments in Libya,
and elements of that organization have been in touch with tribes in the southeastern part of the country. These
officials are concerned that in a post-Qaddafi Libya, France and other western European countries must move
quickly to ensure that the new government does not allow AQUA and others to set up small, semi- autonomous
local entities—or "Caliphates"—in the oil and gas producing regions of southeastern Libya.)
These knowledgeable sources add that the insurgents have the following weapons stockpiled in Benghazi:
82 and 120 mm. mortars;
GPZ type machine guns;
12.7mm. machine guns mounted on 4x4 vehicles;
some anti-aircraft batteries type ZSU 23/2 and 23/4 as well as Man-Portable Air-Defense Systems
(MANPADS) type SAM?;
some tanks type T-72;
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739594
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045019
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739594
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
Possibly some fixed wing aircraft, and some light transporthnedim helicopters.
A seemingly endless supply of AK47 assault rifles and ammunition (even for systems ZSU 23/4 and 23/2).
French, British and Egyptian Special Forces troops are training the rebels inside of western Egypt, and to a
limited degree in the western suburbs of Benghazi.
(Source Comment: These sources add that the MANPAD SAM7 systems appear to be old and badly preserved.
and have been judged useless by the rebels.)
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739594
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045020
Fyi
--
Both Gates and I said the same on the Sunday shows.
My lYi was referring to the Libyan. The arming the rebels breathlessness is silly.
—
Pis let me know what Phil finds out asap. Thx.
One for the wall...
For what it's worth, I am VERY dubious about arming the Libyan rebels. Our best bet is to keep pressure on BOTH sides
to force a diplo solution. Aryls
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739622
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-5CB0045026
FYI — should take care of the job.
Prom: Rhodes, Benjamin 1
Sent Wednesday, March 30, 2011 8:15 PM
To: Sullivan, Jacob]; Reines, Philippe
Subject FIN: Statement by the Press Secretary
B6
