The Washington Post
December 4, 2012 Tuesday
Regional Edition
SECTION: EDITORIAL COPY; Pg. A25
HEADLINE: It's not about Rice
BYLINE: Richard Cohen
BODY:
In 1953, an Army officer by the name of Irving Peress was promoted from captain to major. Peress was a
leftist, possibly a communist, and word of his advancement in rank reached Sen. Joseph McCarthy in
Washington. He asserted that the promotion proved the Army was "soft on communism," and he launched an
investigation that transfixed the nation. Peress, by the way, was a mere dentist. He was the Susan Rice of his
day.
Rice, of course, is a much more substantial figure. She is the U.N. ambassador, a friend of Barack Obama's
and a member of his Cabinet. Still, the attack on her is so disproportionate to what she is accused of having
done - just what was it, exactly? - that as in the Peress case, you have to conclude that there is something more
at work.
At first, I thought we were witnessing just another example of Sen. John McCain (R-Ariz.) doing his
Rumpelstiltskin number - throwing a fit and stomping his feet. It was McCain who first leveled the solemn
charge that Rice had lied to the Sunday TV shows about the attack on the U.S. consulate in Benghazi, Libya.
She had characterized it as a spontaneous riot when it was, in fact, a planned attack by a local al-Qaeda affiliate.
But Rice was hewing to the early line established by the intelligence community. If the CIA and others were
wrong - or deceptive - then so, inevitably, was she.
Just as surely as day follows night, McCain's broadside was echoed by Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.). It
was soon taken up by 97 Republicans in the House who found Rice unqualified to become secretary of state - a
post to which she has not been nominated. "Ambassador Rice is widely viewed as having willfully or
incompetently misled the American public," they bellowed.
I think Rice would make a dandy secretary of state. She's close to the president, and that matters a great
deal. But she is also seen as overly political and that, as much as her version of Benghazi, is what troubles some
others. Oddly enough, Sen. John Kerry (D-Mass.), a former presidential candidate and another potential
secretary of state, is seen as much more of a statesmen. He is indeed an independent foreign-policy thinker who
has, as in days of old, restored the prestige and importance of the Foreign Relations Committee, of which he is
chairman.
But the awful truth is that it hardly matters who Obama chooses. Foreign policy is run from the White
House and not the State Department. Hillary Clinton is about to retire, and while she has done a commendable
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739841
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045821
B6
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739841
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
job at Foggy Bottom, we cannot expect the inevitable book by her to reveal a Clinton Doctrine. For the most
part, she executed, not initiated, foreign policy.
So what is this fuss all about? Not Rice, that's for sure. It has turned instead into an expression of unease
about Obarna's foreign policy and its politicization. The unfortunate Peress came to personify the government's
alleged indifference to the (equally alleged) communist infiltration of the military and virtually everything else
(with the possible exception of the American Legion), Similarly, Rice has become the personification of
unhappiness with the use of intelligence leaks to buff Obanaa's foreign policy image and the conducting of an
amorphous foreign policy. Like Churchill's famous pudding, it lacks theme.
Syria is an example. U.S. inaction has allowed the crisis to fester. Bashar al-Assad's regime might be
dusting off its formidable arsenal of chemical weapons, further evidence of how chaotic this crisis has become,
but much of the time the White House has just trailed after Turkey or France. The war has spread, a refugee
calamity has developed, 40,000 people have died, and jihadists have come to play a prominent role. The Obarna
administration has been as lethargic on Syria as it initially was with Libya.
This sense of an aimless foreign policy, one lacking any moral fervor (or fiber) irritates conservatives much
more than liberals. It certainly enrages McCain, who cannot stomach the big guys kicking little guys around. He
sees an administration that will not engage the American people on matters of foreign policy - make a case for
intervention, not just say it's too hard to do.
The attack on Rice is unfair and excessive. But the issue is not the person but what she represents - in this
case, the administration's 'mobility to articulate a foreign policy that marries American morality to American
power, not merely American politics.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739841
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045822
December na, 2012
For: Hillary
Fysa - calling shortly
 
Sidney Blumenthal
Wednesday, December 19, 2012 9:01 AM
H: Sure you've seen all this info, but start on graph 5. Sid
B6
http://www.juancole.com/2012/12/benghazis-criticizes-consular.ht I
Benghazi's Deep Throat fingers Islamist Leaders for
Attacks as State Dept Criticized on Consular Security
Posted on 12/19/2012 by Juan
The report saying that security was inadequate at the compound that the US had adopted as its ad hoc
consulate in 13enghazio Libya dominates today's headlines. That conclusion is obvious. The
"consulate" was just a private residence taken over for this purpose by the US in the city, It was not
constructed to be a US government building in a potentially hostile city.
I met a person who worked there when I was in Benghazi in June, and she told me that it wasn't even
clear if the consulate would be retained after the first of this year It was possibly temporary,
depending on Congressional funding. (The Tea Party House hasn't been good on meeting requests for
embassy security funds).
The more interesting question than why ad hoc arrangements should have been made for a consulate
during and after the Libyan revolution (the answer to which seems fairly obvious) is, who is
responsible for the string of assassinations and acts of violence in the city, of which the RPG attack on
the consulate on September 11 was only one? Benghazi, with a population of over one million in a
country of 6.5 million, is Libya's second largest city and1/1
e'as the epicenter of the revolution against the
government of Muammar Qaddafi in 2011.
On November 22, Benghazi police chief Farej Darssi was assassinated. In October a police colonel
barely avoided death— his car was wired to explode, A Libyan intelligence officer was killed in
September. A general was assassinated in August. Some of these figures had worked for Qaddafi but
had defected to the revolution. Qaddafi's security forces were responsible for the 1996 massacre of
hardline fundamentalists at Abu Salim prison, and for making others just disappear, Likely the same
shadowy cells that attacked the US consulate are behind the attacks on Benghazi police and army
officers.
There may have been a break in the case. Last Saturday, Benghazi security forces loyal to the elected
government in Tripoli, captured a man they suspected of being involved with the groups behind the
violence. And, he appears to have been willing to spill the beans. So let's call him the Libyan Deep
Throat.
Deep Throat is so knowledgeable about the conspiracies facing the city and so dangerous to those
hatching them that the latter immediately attempted to spring him from jail.
On Sunday morning, militants attacked the police facility next to the holding cell where the man is
being detained. A policeman at that station died in a hail of bullets from the attackers, and they called
for back-up. The police car that sped to the scene as ambushed and three policemen in it were killed.
Still, the police stood their ground and fought off the assault, and they kept their valuable suspect in
custody, with all his valuable testimony.
Shortly after midnight, on Monday morning, small explosives were set off at the Garyounis police
station in Benghazi, damaging a couple of automobiles but otherwise doing little damage. Then
explosives were set off at al-Uruba police station, which also took sniper fire, but neither resulted in
casualties.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739848
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045830
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739848
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
The police became vigilant, and they apprehended a shady-looking man skulking around near the al-
Hadaeg police station, finding him to have two rocket propelled grenades in his possession, which he
was apparently intending to fire at the station.
In other words, the capture of Libyan Deep Throat has set off a gang war on the police, who are being
informed by bombings and shootings that they must let their informant go or risk their
So what is Deep Throat saying? According to local journalist Mohamed Bujenah of the Libyan Herald,
a senior figure in the Benghazi police told him that the informant had fingered as many as 7
prominent Muslim fundamentalist leaders in connection with these attacks, of whom the police
named 6 explicitly:
1 Sufyan Ben Qumu, from the notoriously radical town of Derna, and a former prisoner at
Guantanamo
2.Ahmad Bukatela, leader of the ',Thai& Militia
3.Muhammad al-Zahawi, head of the Ansar al-Sharia militia
4.Muhammad al-Gharabi, a leader of the Rafallala al-Sahati Militia
5.Ismail Sallabi, another leader of Rafallah al-Sahati
6.Salim .Nabous, head of the Zawiya Martyrs' Brigade
It is just a newspaper article. We don't know if the informant actually named these individuals or if he
did so to escape torture, in which case we can't trust what he said. But if the allegations are true, there
is collusion among several hardline militias in the city to create instability in hopes of taking it over.
The new, elected, prime minister Ali Zeidan, has started asserting himself militarily. He closed the
country's southern borders against instability in the Sahel. He may well have some risky house
cleaning to do in Benghazi.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739848
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045831
Dear Bill and Tom,
I'm sorry that I cannot be on the Hill today as we had long planned, but very grateful that you both will be. The
Department and I appreciate your leadership everyday.
So, I'll be nursing my cracked head and cheering you on as you "remain calm and carry on"!
Happy Holidays--H
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739849
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045832
So nice
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Thursday, December 20, 2012 7:40 AM
RE: Thank you so much
Many thanks. Will do my best. Get well soon, and have a wonderful holiday. I'm very lucky to serve in your State
Department.
Thanks I wish I could tell u I am looking forward to this but it would be a lie! Get better...
----
Well, what doesn't kill you, makes you stronger gas I have rationalized for years), so just survive and you'll have
triumphed!
----
FYSA
Prom: Laszczych, Joanne
Sent: Thursday, December 20, 2012 7:57 AM
To: Mills, Cheryl D
Subject: FOX from Caitlin
VAN SUSTEREN: Senator, there is a report from the State Department that Secretary of State Hillary
Clinton will testify on Benghazi before the middle of January. There has been some criticism of whether or
not she has a concussion. I believe she has a concussion. What do you think?
MCCAIN: I know that in my view, Secretary Clinton, when she said she assumed full responsibility, she
certainly has a lot of responsibility for what happened in Benghazi. That's -- that report made that very
clear. But I must say, I have never seen Secretary Clinton back down from a fight. And I have
never seen her back down. And / believe that she is now not physically well enough to testify
and she will testify the middle of January.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739855
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045837
Huma called him and Graham. Also, someone should call Greta VS to thank her for "knowing the truth."
Can you call me?
Fyi.
Thanks.
Sullivan, Jacob J <Sullivanii@state.gov>
Thursday, December 20, 2012 1:25 PM
RE: H: Sure you've seen all this info, but start on graph 5. Sid
From H [rnallto:HDR220cliritonernail.com]
Sent: Thursday, December 20, 2012 12:40 PM
To Sullivan, Jacob 3
Subject Fw: H: Sure you've seen all this info, but start on graph 5. Sid
Fyi.
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Thursday, December 20 2012 1:52 PM
'sullivanjj@state.gov'
Fw: H: Libya, latest Benghazi intel. Sid
hrc memo libya, benghazi, oil 121012,docx
More info.
 
Verveer, Melanne S <VerveerMS@state.gov>
Tuesday, December 7, 2010 4:52 PM
Fw: latest B1
1.4(D)
PVerveer B6
Friday, December 17, 2010 12:12 AM
From B6
Please
let me know if I can be of any help to your department and will happy to do and please thank
Mrs. Hillary Clinton on behalf of me and
. supporting Afghan women.
•Thank you,
B6
B6
B6
B6
B6
B6
B6
B6
