H <hrod17@clintonemaiLcom>
Wednesday, July 4, 2012 7:54 AM
'sullivanjj@state.gov'
Fw: H: Libyan elections intel. Sid
hrc memo libyan elections intel 070312.docx
More info.
B6
Another report--
SOURCE: Sources with direct access to the Libyan National Transitional Council, as well as the highest levels of
European Governments, and Western Intelligence and security services.
1. As of the morning of July 6, an individual with access to the information stated in confidence that Libyan National
Transitional Council (NTC) President Mustafa Abdel Jalil remains committed to a transfer of power to a popularly elected
government; however, he is prepared to ex-tend the life of the NTC as a guarantor of stability for the Libyan people
following the July 7, 2012 election for seats in a 200-member General National Congress (GNC). Jaifi realizes that 2.7
million Libyans have registered to vote and are generally anxious to replace the increasingly unpopular NTC. That said,
JAI expects the voting to lead to a period of confusion and he will not abandon his authority until the results are fixed.
2. Jalil is also frustrated by the fact that during its eight-month tenure of the administration of Prime Minister Abclel
Rahman el-Keib - who was appointed by the NTC was unable to provide solutions for Libya's long list of needs: a
functioning justice system, a reconciliation process for officials who served the old administration, the disarming of
militia, building functional national security forces, rebuilding destroyed areas, and delivering basic services such as
healthcare.
3. At the same time, outside of the oil sector, much of Libya's economy is stagnant, and in the opinion of Western
security officials, lacks the government's go-ahead to restart public sector infrastructure contracts. In addition,
international advisers and foreign investors are reluctant to return to an environment where the government will not
sign long term agreements and cannot guarantee security.
4.(Source Comment: According to an extremely sensitive source, Jalil continues to believe that this chaotic situation
should not be surprising. He regularly points out that eight months is not a sufficient amount of time to build functioning
institutions from the remnants of the regime of former dictator Muammar al Qaddafi. The old regime featured a
dysfunctional bureaucracy, idiosyncratic rule, and anti-institutionalism. Additionally, Jaill now re
Ializes that due to
pronounced incompetence and a lack of will to take unpopular decisions the el-Keib government also failed to make
progress in the few areas where it could have achieved meaningful change. The towns of Sirte and Tawargha are
representative of the situation in the countryside where people lost their homes in the conflict and have been living in
temporary camps with limited ability to register and vote in their home district. Jalil has been urged by contacts in the
French and Italian Governments to guarantee the rights of people across the country in particular, he has serious
concerns as to whether or not supporters of former dictator Muammar al Qaddafi in his hometown of Sirte will be
included in the future political processes of the new Libya; if they are not allowed to vote by local militiamen. At the
same time, the fighting between Libyan Arabs and Tebta tribesmen in the Kufra area threatens to prevent any voting
there. Jalil has been warned that the NTC regulations now state that members of the National Army are not allowed to
vote or run for office, which is a disincentive for armed militia brigade members to become legitimate soldiers.)
5.This well informed individual believes that despite these flaws, the new government created by the July 7 election will
eventually have the mandate to take the difficult decisions that can create a reconciliation process. Jalil will work to
maintain order in this transition period, and finally reach his goal of creating a situation where the government can
rebuild homes and restore sufficient law and order; allowing those in Sirte, Tawargha, Kufra, and throughout the rest of
the country to live in their hometowns, establishing a situation where a true civil society can develop.
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739882
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045193
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739882
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
6. Jail!, in conversations with the leaders of the Muslim Brotherhood (MB), and separately with liberal leader Ali
Tarhouni, has acknowledged that the central government's top priority must be security and that the NTC has been
unable to provide it. That said, Jail! and Minister of Defense Ousarna alefuwali have pledged to provide 30,000 to 40,000
security personnel for election day to prevent similar incidents to the July 1 attack on Benghazi's election headquarters.
In that case eastern federalists entered the building, where ballot papers were burned and ballot boxes destroyed.
Similarly, these federalist forces are suspected of the attack on July 5 that burned down Ajdabiya's main storage centre
for election materials.
7. In the opinion of this individual, although those responsible for the Benghazi attack were pro-federalist, it has not
been proven that they were members of the self-appointed Cyrenaican National Council (MC), whose military arm set
up a roadblock in Wadi al-Ahmar on Libya's major east-west highway to demand that Cyrenaica get as many seats in the
GNC as Tripolitania. Thus far, neither the CNC nor any other group has publicly stated that they intend to use violence to
disrupt the elections. (Note: Under the current system Tripolitania will have 120 seats in the GNC, Cyrenaica (Barge) 62,
and Fezzan in the South 18.)
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739882
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER. STATE-SCB0045194
Will pass to Chris and Beth. To state the obvious, the ballot burning and helicopter shootdown are concerning.
Fyi
B6
U.S. Department of State
Case No. F-2015-04841
Doc No. C05739885
Date: 05/13/2015
STATE DEPT. - PRODUCED TO HOUSE SELECT BENGHAZI COMM.
SUBJECT TO AGREEMENT ON SENSITIVE INFORMATION & REDACTIONS. NO FOIA WAIVER.
RELEASE IN
PART B6
