Do you know where my pt instruction sheets are?
Pis send
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Wednesday, July 1, 2009 8:26 PM
'JilotyLC@state.gov'; 'Russorv@state.gov'
Fw:
a letter of congrats and good wishes.
Ok
That is a huge group. There is no way to make them all feel important and listened to. Should we split group in half and
have two lunches?
Ok
Oh, dear. I guess I'd rather leave at 2 but does that present problems I don't know about?
Ok that's when I will go. Is that certain?
Does GOH see the food coming in and know we are delivering?
What does this mean?
What's Hussein like?
I can do it before noon tomorrow or on Sunday.
Ok if can be done before 1.
Can you set up Nakasone call?
Use this to emphasize to Denis the importance of OAS position. Do you know ifFwould take it again? B6
 
I am calling Tom.
Can you talk? What time is best?
may still be out of country. Other names:
If we can't get anyone of stature, then I think it should be
drivers w lots of outside help.
Also, when will I receive next draft of speech?
I'm seeing Santa at 8:30 so won't take off until closer to 9:30. Is that ok?
I'm willing to see him whenever.
So sad and terrible. We should ask Chris Hill to raise this w govt. If we ever get Posner confirmed we should emphazise
LGBT human rights.
Are you in Haiti already?
As to the QDDR, I think we should task the Building and AID to contribute. I have some ideas about that which I will talk
to Jack and Jake about.
Let me know how it goes w the trip.
 
Thx.
Did he ask to speak to me? I didn't reach out to him but I'm willing to talk once I get points. Is Zelaya confirmed for
tomorrow? I didn't see him on schedule so did it just happen?
Let's do Uribe tonight.
Ok to connect.
I need time on Thursday or Friday to see Holbrooke.
Mark Hyman is in town Wed and Thurs and I'd like to see him.
Also, did you set up a time for him to see me when he's in DC?
 
 
Do either of you have his email or cell info?
What are emails for Kurt Campbell and Tom Donilon?
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Saturday, July 11, 2009 8:08 PM
Fw: N. Korea
Fyi.
I am nearly done w my editing (along w Bill's). Pls send me all the commerts you just listed so I can review.
I'm reviewing all of the edits you forwarded and will incorporate many. Jim Kennedy, as always, was fabulous. I should
have my revision ready tomorrow. Thx.
Jake---Pls review, do some recon outreach and advise what, if anything, we should do. Thx. H
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Tuesday, July 14, 2009 5:35 AM
'Imuscatine
Re: CFR draft
Thanks so much. Pls send it to me at same time so I can review as well.
Pls print for me.
Pis call Joe and ask him for Judy Rupert's email and phone info. When you have it, pis call or email her to tell her how to
contact me.
Is there a telepromter I can use tomorrow?
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com >
Tuesday, July 14, 2009 9:46 AM
'Imuscatine
Re: CFR latest draft
It is getting better. I've gone thru it once and will be ready to discuss later. Thank you s000 much.
I think we have to mention
B5
How's it coming?
Ok.
Pls add as option: April 25--EMILY'S LIST 25th anniversary.
 
What did WH say?
It is markedly better. But, as I'm reading thru it, I notice missing words and what appear to be gaps as a result of editing.
Could you pls read carefully and could we talk in about 30 minutes?
Should we wait until you send me the cleaned up version?
Can you also fax one to Bill at home in NY? Do you have #?
Pis let me know when you send--I'm having fax trouble.
Can you fax to me?
I can't print email so pis fax. Thx.
My fax is broken! So Huma is coming to print for me. I'm trying to conference you and Jake to discuss. Thx.
I think Huma is on the way. Thx. Let's go ahead abd talk now, as soon as ops gets it ready
•
Thx for
ALL your help.
I thought we cancelled the management mtg? Also, did you tell Sarah F I might not get there until 10:30?
Check w Holbrooke-
Derek---Thank you for all of your help and leadership on the speech and the policies it embodies. It is a delight working
w you. All the best, Hillary
Pis print.
Burns--thank you for forwarding this request. I always want Tony Campolo (and Peggy) to be able to find me. I'm copying
my assistant, Lauren Jiloty, so she can give you her info for contact purposes. All the best, H
Jake--i told you yesterday, but it bears repeating--you're doing a wonderful job. Not just on the speech, but all the work
to establish and implement the priorities it represents. I'm very grateful---Hillary
Can we implement his suggestion about pooling donors?
Thx for sending. I've forwarded to Jake Sullivan in my office to follow up.
Ok. Let's discuss this and my "list" over the weekend. Can we set time for meeting?
Let's do tomorrow after MTP. Ok?
Ok.
Done
Done.
I still don't have my MTP briefing.
Ok. Is Kristy in town? If so, can I see her tomorrow?
I reed the two books for the SED but nothing for MTP. Will it arrive soon?
Fyi
Ok. Thx.
Do you have my call list? I'm looking for Joe Duffy/Anne Wexler number.
Thx.
Is the 50k figure State and AID?
Kurdistan election results?
Can you find out for me how many Nazi prison camps we had in US during WW2 and what we did w the detainees--did
we ever try any? Did we deport them after war ended?
Re Sudan: how do you pronounce Abyei?
What is % and dollar increase in 2010 budget for ops and aid?
I don't understand the answer to the prostitution policy question. What's the simplest way to say it?
Ok--but when are we scheduled top talk? Also pls send me five main points of my speech to summarize our goals. I want
to reference them.
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com >
Sunday, Jul26, 2009 7:53 AM
'preine
Re: Questions
Thx. I meant budget question to refer to overall budget. Can you get that for me?
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Sunday, July 26, 2009 12:41 PM
'abedinh@state.gov'
Re: for HRC
Thx so much for your help--and for Ernie Banks! Let's play two!!
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Sunday, July 26, 2009 1:52 PM
'SBerger
Re:
Thx so much for all of your help.
•
Thx so much for all of your help. — Reason: 1.4(B), 1.4(D) — Declassify on: 07/25/2024
Thx so much for all of your help.
ri-ux
B6
Thx for all of your help. And I'd love to talk soon. I'll start trying to find a time.
Thx for all of your help.
Thx for the feedback and for everything you did to make it happen.
Sorryl hit send too soon!
Sorry I hit send too soon!
Will the DCA team be in Columbia in early August? I thought we had set that up but heard today they might not get
there until September. What's the plan?
Pls put
RELEASE IN PART
B6
H <hrod17@clintonemail.com>
Friday, July 31, 2009 3:25 PM
'JilotyLC@state.gov'; 'Russorv@state.gov'
Fw: Braval
on call list and do letter to her wishing her well etc. B6
Pis print.
Thanks so much. But all the positive feedback is worrying! Loved seeing you the other night.
Will the DCA team be in Columbia in early August? I thought we had set that up but heard today they might not get
there until September. What's the plan?
Sorry I hit send too soon!
Will the DCA team be in Columbia in early August? I thought we had set that up but heard today they might not get
there until September. What's the plan?
Pls pu )n call list and do letter to her wishing her well etc. B6
 
Pis print.
This should moot request to hrc:
IRAN
President Ahmadinejad canceled his trip to an African Union summit in Lydia. No reason was given for his decision.
(Reuters)
1
8:35 am PRESIDENTIAL DAILY BRIEFING
8:45 am Secretary's Office
8:45 am DAILY MEETING w/SENIOR STAFF
9:15 am Secretary's Conference Room
9:15 am PHOTO w/JOSE VILLARREAL, NOMINEE FOR COMMISSIONER
9:25 am GENERAL, SHANGHAI EXPO 2010 Secretary's Outer Office
9:25 am PHOTO OP w/ WANDA, GREGORY, & NATIKA WASHINGTON
Secy's Outer Office *Natilca works for Lew Lukens, Wanda and Gregory are her parents.
9:30 am BIWEEKLY MEETING w/MANAGEMENT TEAM
10:00 am Deputy Secretary's Conference Room
10:10 am DEPART State Department *En route White House
10:15 am ARRIVE White House
10:15 am WEEKLY MEETING w/GENERAL JONES AND SECRETARY GATES
10:45 am White House Situation Room
10:50 am SMALL GROUP MEETING
11:45 am White House Situation Room
11:45 am DEPART White House *En route State Department
11:50 am ARRIVE State Department
12:00 pm SWEARING IN CEREMONY FOR US AMBASSADOR TO IRELAND,
12:20 pm DANIEL ROONEY Treaty Room *Approx. 30 ppl. expected.
12:30 pm HOLD FOR HUMA/OFFICE TIME
1:30 pm Secretary's Office
1:30 pm MEETING w/SE RICHARD MORNINGSTAR
2:00 pm Secretary's Office
2:00pm MEETING w/AMB. DAVID CHOQUEHUANCA, MINISTER OF FOREIGN
2:30 pm AFFAIRS, BOLIVIA Secy's Conf. Room *Camera Spray in Treaty Room preceding.
2:45pm MEETING w/ASSISTANT SECRETARY ERIC SCHWARTZ
3:15 pm Secretary's Office
3:15 pm HOLD FOR ROSEMARIE
3:20 pm SCHEDULING MEETING w/HUMA AND LONA
3:45pm Secretary's Office
4:15 pm PRIVATE MEETING w/EILEEN CHAMBERLIN DONOHOE
4:30 pm Secretary's Office
4:30 pm MEETING w/PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY PRIME MINISTER
5:15 pm SALAM FAYYAD Secretary's Outer Office *Camera Spray in Treaty Room preceding.
5:20 pm DEPART State Department "En Route White House.
5:30 pm ARRIVE White House
5:30 pm WEEKLY MEETING w/ POTUS
6:00 pm Secretary's Office
5:50 pm DEPART State Department "En route Private Residence
2
6:00 pm ARRIVE Private Residence ###
3
Madam Secretary - I just confirmed that you sent a thank you note to Mexican FM Patricia Espinosa Cantellano
4
 
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Thursday, July 02, 2009 8:48 AM
Fw: DPRK launches two short-range missiles (U)
I will prepare for you to sign on Monday.
8
Great - will call you b/f noon
10
I actually think that's better, we had entertained it but didn't know what u would be up for. Will proceed.
 
Pdb on the way
Also, there's a secpres from rch that needs ur signature.
13
Printing and sending to u hrc
Esther brimmer and jake report that the IAEA board has just elected Amano by a vote of 23-11-1. The presumed
abstention is Argentina. The abstention brought the required vote down to 23 from 24.
15
The g3 is delayed till 5pm wheels up
There is a lear available at 2pm with 6 seats.
Do u want to just leave at 5?
16
 
18
2pm is now no longer an option. Only option is 5pm wheels up.
- pls call jake when u can thru ops. He has a few things to report
- Holbrooke called me this morning with a point that hasn't been presented to u. He doesn't think u absolutely have to
do camps if u go to pak. He thinks a short visit with officials, just a few hours doing bilateral things is sufficient and
talking about idps while u r in country will more than make the point. Something else to consider as u make ur decision.
20
Yes confirmed.
Call with chris hill and jake is scheduled for 2pm. Ops will connect to house.
22
U may have talked to him cause he called direct too. But jones left message on my cell about an hour ago.
23
Call with chris hill moved to 230 instead. He's still with Maliki
24
Read traffic all the way down
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD©state.gov>
Thursday, July 02, 2009 3:24 PM
Fw: 2009-07-01 Draft letter to G0h re 57m pledge (4)
2009-07-01 Draft letter to G0h re 57m pledge (4).docx
Draft of cable going to preval in advance of our visit.
I don't know what would take so long to begin. B5
Cdm
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Thursday, July 02, 2009 4:33 PM
Fw: King Abdullah names Prince Hussein Crown Prince
 
Isn't a surprise since 5 years ago he removed his brother as official crown prince.
Basically he's not honoring his fathers dying wish but since constitution says it should be son (with brother as option) he
has clear authority to do it. I personally think this shows confidence in his position as he's not worried about an outcry
from his fathers loyalists.
Well he's very young, only 15.
Rumor is hes smart, quiet, bookish. Like his father.
What is interesting is that the reason abdullah gave from removing his brother 5 years ago is that he thought the weight
of being crown prince restricted his life, education and travel. I suspect the reason he's done this is so his son can be
properly groomed from now to inherit the thrown. Life will change dramatically for him.
Schumer returned your call.
Would like to download to you on latest with kirsten/carolyn before u talk to him.
33
Just rtnd your call, she will be available on her cell/at home tonight and thru the weekend.
###
34
Fyi
Sent via BlackBerry by AT&T
Fyi
Sent via BlackBerry by AT&T
 
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Thursday, July 02, 2009 8:04 PM
Fw: Schumer
Fyi on schumer call.
Fyi
Nita lowey also just called again. Said she's going into an event and will be out of pocket for a few hours.
Ops just faxed a call sheet for Aliyev to house. Steinberg will be traveling to Baku on July 10, and Jim/Jake/phil think the
call from you will help to pave the way for his trip. There is an info memo on latest developments, a cable summary, and
a bio. You ok with proceeding with setting up call? We can do over next few days if u r ok.
Pdb coming on secure fax at 10am.
Call with president aliyev has been confirmed for 10am. Ops will call you.
39
Nita lowey called for you.
Also sending thru a nakasone call sheet. It suggests that you call after the IAEA Board formally acclaims Amano's
election. The meeting to do that is going on now in Vienna, so we will let you know after the election is formally
acclaimed so call can be scheduled if ok with you.
40
As soon as we get word, we can.
Will reach out and see if he can do it at noon.
Fyi
B6
 
 
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Friday, July 03, 2009 11:21 PM
Fw: North Korea fires third missile (SBU)
I have just asked for the state of play this am as messages continued last night until lam.
The bottom line of all of them was not dissimiliar to this message from torn so forwarding this one - namely, all had been
unsuccessful in dissuading Zeleya from going today and several leaders and fm (espinoza) thought call from you might
help but Zeleya appeared in update messages to get more resolute as evening went on to return based upon readouts of
various meetings with him.
Cdm
I just spoke to torn (see b/1)..
•He thinks for the moment a call by you is not indicated - first, Zeleya was unpersuadable by 2am by even his closet allies
and second, torn said folks appear to stepping away from him.
He intends to fly mid-day so there will be plenty of time for more discussion over next several hours.
Cdm
Will call you now
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Sunday, July 05, 2009 11:09 AM
Fw: Security Situation
Fyi - calling you
As prelude
Fyi
B6
Here's what likely makes the most sense.
I will feel out re whehter he would like to take this on and if so, what time he could give to it.
We set up a town hall with building for weds or thurs at which you announce the effort. This gives philippe and pj the
b/g of week to lay press ground work so we get the coverage we want.
If this makes sense to you, I am going to reach out to
Cdm
You will get a draft of speech tomorrow - will go through list of recs and discuss with jack/jake
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Sunday, July 05, 2009 8:37 PM
Sullivan, Jacob J
Fw: Conference call
Fyi
Fyi
Yes I will let them know now.
Fyi B6
Taking off now.
Talked to jake and derek - draft will be to you in am b/c they are doing so changes today. We'll get to you by email and
hard copy by 9am
86
 
Sorry yes exactly
We have shy tomorrow at 10am too.
 
I faxed a new, slightly revised version of the speech to your house. It is also attached.
92
 
Colombian president alvaro uribe just called through ops. Said he's available anytime tonite to talk. Am trying to track
down points for you from tom/jake but since u r seeing zelaya tomorrow, I assume u want to do this tonite?
96
Zelaya tentatively on for 1 (but we understand it might fall thru) but we are currently planning on it.
Uribe is asking to talk to you. He's available the rest of the evening and we can also do tomorrow morning but he didn't
confirm availability for tomorrow. I've asked tom and jake for points for u.
These are notes from torn. Let me know if u are ok with ops connecting call.
Sounds good, will follow up.
I have an email into him asking what time of day works best.
http://www.quinnipiac.edu/x1284.xml?ReleaselD=1347&What=&strArea=;&strTime=0
hnt this page Close window
Release Detail
July 7, 2009 - Obama's Approval Drops In Ohio - Critical Swing State, Quinnipiac University Poll Finds;
2010 Senate Race Tips Slightly To Democrats
Word format
President Barack Obama gets a lackluster 49 - 44 percent approval rating in Ohio, considered by many to be the
most important swing state in a presidential election, according to a Quinnipiac University poll released today.
This is President Obama's lowest approval rating in any national or statewide Quinnipiac University poll since
he was inaugurated and is down from 62 - 31 percent in a May 6 survey.
By a small 48 - 46 percen t margin, voters disapprove of the way Obama is handling the economy, the
independent Quinnipiac (KWIN-uh-pe-ack) University poll finds. This is down from a 57 - 36 percent approval
May 6. A total of 66 percent of Ohio voters are "somewhat dissatisfied" or "very dissatisfied" with the way
things are going in the state, while 33 percent are "very satisfied" or "somewhat satisfied," numbers that haven't
changed since Obama was elected.
In the race for Ohio's U.S. Senate seat being vacated by retiring George Voinovich in 2010, Lee Fisher and
Jennifer Brunner remain neck-and-neck for the Democratic nomination and both would defeat any of the GOP
candidates if the election were today.
"The economy in Ohio is as bad as anywhere in America. These numbers indicate that for the first time voters
have decided that President Barack Obama bears some responsibility for their problems," said Peter A. Brown,
assistant director of the Quinnipiac University Polling Institute.
"Until now voters have given President Obama high ratings on the economy, blaming former President George
W. Bush for their problems. They might be taking out their frustration on President Obama, possibly deciding
that the change he promised has not come as quickly as they expected."
"Ohio historically has been the prototypical swing state. One of the reasons Barack Obama won the p residency
by such a wide margin is that he carried Ohio with 52 percent of the vote and captured the lion's share of
independent votes," Brown added.
"Now, by a 48 - 46 percent margin, Ohio independent voters give the President a failing grade on the economy.
These numbers indicate that he may be losing, at least for now, some of those who voted for him in November
and should be an indication to the White House that his honeymoon with the voters may be ending."
In the Senate race, Lt. Gov. Lee Fisher holds a 24 - 21 percent lead over Secretary of State Jennifer Brunner in
the race for the Democratic nomination, with 51 percent undecided.
Former U.S. Rep. Rob Portman holds a 33 - 10 percent lead over car dealer Tom Ganley on the Republican
side, with 55 percent undecided.
In general election trial heats, Brunner would defeat Ganley 35 - 31 percent and get 35 percent to Portman's 34
percent. Fisher leads Ganley 36 - 30 percent and Portman 37 - 33 percent.
From June 26 - July 1, Quinnipiac University surveyed 1,259 Ohio voters, with a margin of error of +/- 2.8
percentage points. The survey includes 483 Democrats with a margin of error of +/- 4.5 percentage points and
445 Republicans with a margin of error of +/-4.7 percentage points.
The Quinnipiac University Poll, directed by Douglas Schwartz, Ph.D., conducts public opinion surveys in
Florida, Pennsylvania, New York, New Jersey, Connecticut, Ohio and the nation as a public service and for
research. For more data and RSS feed - http://www.quinnipiac.edu/polling.xml, or (203) 582-5201.
2. (If registered Republican) As you may know, Ohio Senator George Voinovich will not be running for
reelection in 2010. Thinking about the 2010 Republican primary for United States Senator, if the 2010
Republican primary for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Rob Portman and
Tom Ganley, for whom would you vote?
REGISTERED REPS..
Tot Men Worn
Portman 33% 39% 25%
Ganley 10 11 9
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 1 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 2 3 -
DK/NA 55 46 ' 65
TREND: (If registered Republican) As you may know, Ohio Senator George Voinovich will not be running for
reelection in 2010. Thinking about the 2010 Republican primary for United States Senator, if the 2010
Republican primary for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Rob Portman and
Tom Ganley, for whom would you vote? (*Someone Else & Wouldn't Vote volunteered options not in option
list)
REGISTERED REPUBLICANS
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4
2009 2009 2009 2009*
Portman 33 29 31 33
Ganley 10 8 na na
Taylor na 8 14 11
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 1 1 1 -
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 2 1 1 -
DK/NA 55 54 52 56
3. (If registered Democrat) Thinking about the 2010 Democratic primary for United States Senator, if the 2010
Democratic primary for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Lee Fish er and
Jennifer Brunner, for whom would you vote?
REGISTERED DEMS..
Tot Men Worn
Fisher 24% 31% 20%
Brunner 21 26 • 18
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 2 - 2
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 3 1 4
DK/NA 51 42 56
TREND: (If registered Democrat) Thinking about the 2010 Democratic primary for United States Senator, if
the 2010 Democratic primary for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Lee
Fisher and Jennifer Brunner, for whom would you vote? (*Someone Else & Wouldn't Vote volunteered options
not in option list / na=not asked)
REGISTERED DEMOCRATS
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4
2009 2009 2009 2009*
Fisher 24 20 18
18
Brunner 21 16 14 16
Yates na 4 6 na
Ryan na na 12 14
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 2 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 3 1 2
OK/NA 51 59 46 53
6. If the 2010 election for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Lee Fisher the
Democrat and Rob Portman the Republican, for whom would you vote?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglci
Fisher 37% 5% 76% 28% 33% 40% 28%
Portman 33 72 4 31 41 27 44
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 2 - - 3 2 1
1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 2 - 1 3 2 1 1
DR/NA 26 22 19 35 21 31 27
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Fisher 35% 43% 30% 40% 24% 39%
Portman 32 28 25 26 53 40
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 3 1 5 - 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 1 1 4 - 2 3
DR/NA 29 28 36 34 19 17
TREND: If the 2010 election for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Lee
Fisher the Democrat and Rob Portman the Republican, for whom would you vote?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4
2009 2009 2009 2009
Fisher 37 42 41 42
Portman
33 31 33 27
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 2 1 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 2 - 2 1
DK/NA 26 26 24 29
7. If the 2010 election for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Lee Fisher the
Democrat and Tom Ganley the Republican, for whom would you vote?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evngicl
39% 26%
24 43
1 -
1 2
Fisher 36% 5% 73% 26% 32%
Ganley 30 65 4 29 38
SMONE ELSE (VOL) 1 - - 2 2
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 2 1 1 1 2
DK/NA 31 28 22 42=2
0 26 36 29
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Fisher 36% 41% 31% 36% 21% 37%
Ganley 26 31 23 33 34 35
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 2 - 2 - 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 1 1 4 1 2 3
DK/NA 35 26 40 29 41 24
8. If the 2010 election for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Jennifer
Brunner the Democrat and Tom Ganley the Republican, for whom would you vote?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Brunner 35% 6% 71% 23% . 31% 38% 27%
Ganley 31 67 4=2
0 30 38 25 41
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 1 - - 2 . 2 1 -
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 2 2 1 2 3 1 1
DK/NA 31 25 23 44 26 35 31
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Brunner 35% 37% 40% 31% 24% 37%
Ganley 32 30 23 35 34 35
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 1 - 5 - 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) - 3 2 - 3 3
DK/NA 32 30 31 34 38 24
9. If the 2010 election for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Jennifer
Brunner the Democrat and Rob Portman the Republican, for whom would you vote?
20 WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Brunner 35% 5% 71% 26% 31% 39% 25%
Portman 34 72 5 32 42 27 46
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 1 - - 2 2 -
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 1 - - 1 2 1
DR/NA 29 23 23 39 24 33 28
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Brunner 31% 39% 41% 32% 24% 38%
Portman 36 28 22 29 54 39
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 2 - 4 - 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) - 1 2 - 1 3
DK/NA 31 32 31 38 21 20
TREND: If the 2010 electi on for United States Senator were being held today and the candidates were Jennifer
Brunner the Democrat and Rob Portman the Republican, for whom would you vote?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4
2009 2009 2009 2009
Brunner 35 40 39 38 '
Portman 34 32 34 28
SMONE ELSE(VOL) 1 - 1 1
WLDN'T VOTE(VOL) 1 - 2 1
DK/NA 29 27 25 31
14. Is your opinion of- Lee Fisher favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about him?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Favorable 27% 9% 46% 24% 27% 27% 22%
Unfavorable 16 31 4 14 21 11 20
Hvn ' t hrd enough 56 59 50 60 50 61 57
REFUSED 1 1 1 2 2 1 1
TREND: Is your opinion of - Jennifer Brunner favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about her?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4 Dec 10
2009 2009 2009 2009 2008
Favorable 27 31 31 34 26
Unfavorable 16 12 14 10 24
Hvn ' t hrd enough 56 55 55 55 49
REFUSED 1 120 1 1 1
16. Is your opinion of - Rob Portman favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about him?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Wom Evnglcl
Favorable 29% 14% 49% 24% 30% 28% 26%
Unfavorable 17 32 6 15 23 11 20
Hvn ' t hrd enough 53 53 45 59 45 60 53
REFUSED 1 1 1 2 2 1 1
TREND: Is your opinion of - Lee Fisher favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about him?
•
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4 Dec 10
2009 2009 2009 2009 2008
Favorable 29 37 32 33 23
Unfavorable 17 13 13 10 10
Hvn ' t hrd enough 53 48 54 55 66
REFUSED 1 1 1 2 1
15. Is your opinion of - Jennifer Brunner favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about her?
0 WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Favorable 21% 35% 8% 23% 27% 16% 24%
Unfavorable 6 1 9 6 5 6 3
Hvn ' t hrd enough 72 63 82 70 67 77 71
REFUSED 1 1 1 1 1 1 1
TREND: Is your opinion of- Rob Portman favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about him?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4 Dec 10
2009 2009 2009 2009 2008
OA
Favorable 21 22 25 21 12
Unfavorable 6 9 7 6 7
Hvn ' t hrd enough 72 68 67 72 80
REFUSED 1 1 1 1 1
17. Is your opinion of- Tom Ganley favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about him?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem • Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Favorable 12% 19% 6% 11% 14% 10% 14%
Unfavorable 4 2 7 3 5 3 3
Hvn ' t hrd enough 83 78 86 84 79 86 82
REFUSED 1 1 1 2 2 1 . 1
TREND: Is your opinion of - Tom Ganley favorable, unfavorable or haven't you heard enough about him?
Jul 7 May 6
2009 2009
Favorable 12 6
Unfavorable 4 4
Hvn ' t hrd enough 83 89
REFUSED 1 1
19. Do you approve or disapprove of the way George Voinovich is handling his job as United States Senator?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Approve 52% 60% 53% 46% 49% 55% 53%
Disapprove
DK/NA
29 28 23 35 39 21 30
19 13 24 18 13 24 17
Cntrl Nrth
E NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Approve 45% 60% 45% 48% 44% 56%
Disapprove 29 25 31 36 37 .28
DK/NA 26 15 24 16 19 15
TREND: Do you approve or disapprove of the way George Voinovich is handling his job as United States
Senator? (*Also 55% on 2/4/2009)
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4 Dec
APPROVE
High
10 May 6
Low
Dec 13
2009 2009 2009 2009 2008 2009* 2006
Approve 52 55 52 55 51 55 41
Disapprove 29 30 32 29 31 30 33
DK/NA 19 15
16 16 17 15 26
20. Do you approve or disapprove of the way Sherrod Brown is handling his job as United States Senator?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Approve 41% 29% 58% 37% 36% 46% 35%
Disapprove 29 43 12 32 39 19 34
DK/NA 30 28 30 31 24 35 32
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Approve 37% 51% 36% 48% 25% 37%
Disapprove 29 27 22 20 36 32
DK/NA 33 22 41 33 39 30
TREND: Do you approve or disapprove of=2 Othe way Sherrod Brown is handling his job as United States
Senator?
APPROVE
High Low
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb. 4 Dec 10 May 6 Jul 7
.2009 2009 2009 2009 2008 2009 2009
Approve 41 52 48 51 48 52 41
Disapprove 29 24 25 22 26 24 29
DK/NA 30 . 24 27 27 26 24 30
22. Do you approve or disapprove of the way Lee Fisher is handling his job as Ohio's lieutenant governor?
=2
0 WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Approve 39% 26% 58% 32% 38% 40% 35%
Disapprove 24 36 10 23 30 18 30
DK/NA 38 38 32 45 32 42 34
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Approve 35% 42% 31% 59% 30% 42%
Disapprove 23 21 27 14 26 30
DK/NA 42 36 42 27 44 28
TREND: Do you approve or disapprove of the way Lee Fisher is handling his job as Ohio's lieutenant
governor?
Jul 7 May 6
2009 2009
Approve 39 49
Disapprove 24 17
DK/NA 38 33
< br>
23. Do you approve or disapprove of the way Jennifer Brunner is handling her job as Ohio's Secretary of State?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Approve 38% 22% 60% 32% 37% 39% 34%
Disapprove 25 42 7 27 32 18 30
DK/NA 37 36 33 41 30 43 36
WtBrnAgn
•
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Approve 49% 19% 85% 38% 39% 57% 33%
Disapprove 44 75 11 48 53 36 59
DK/NA
8 6 3 14 8 7 8
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Approve 50% 52% 55% 46% 36% 47%
Disapprove 43 39 40 44 60 47
DK/NA 6 10 6 10 4 6
TREND: Do you approve or disapprove of the way Barack Obama is handling his job as president?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 6
2009 2009 2009 2009
Approve 49 62 57 67
Disapprove 44 31 33 16
DK/NA 8 7 11 17
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Approve 36% 44% 44% 40% 28% 33%
Disapprove 29 21 13 21 31 31
DK/NA 36 35 43 39 41 35
TREND: Do you approve or disapprove of the way Jennifer Brunner is handling her job as Ohio's Secretary of
State?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 4 Dec 10 Aug 14 Jun 4
2009 2009 2009 2009 2008 2008 2008
Approve 38 45 41 44 39 38 38
Disapprove 25 20 19 16 28 12 13
DK/NA 37 34 39 41 33 50 48
24. Do you approve or disapprove of the way Barack Obama is handling his job as president?
25. In general, how satisfied are you with the way things are going in Ohio today? Are you very satisfied,
somewhat satisfied, somewhat dissatisfied, or very dissatisfied?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evngicl
Very satisfied 2% 1% 4% 1% 3% 2% 3%
Smwht satisfied 31 22 46 27 28 35 26
Smwht dissatisfied 36 40 31 36 34 38 36
Very dissatisfied 30 36 19 36 34 25 35
DK/NA 1 1 1 1 1 - 1
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Very satisfied 3% 3% - 2% 3% 1%
Smwht satisfied 29 33 32 49 25 28
Smwht dissatisfied 39 35 39 27 39 36
Very dissatisfied 29 29 28 22 33 34
DK/NA - 1 1=2
0 - - 1
TREND: In general, how satisfied are you with the way things are going in Ohio today? Are you very satisfied,
somewhat satisfied, somewhat dissatisfied, or very dissatisfied?
VERY+SMWHT....
High Low
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 17 Feb 5 Dec 11 Mar 21 Mar 17
2009 2009 2009 2009 2008 2007 2009
Very satisfied 2 4 2 2 3 5 2
Smwht satisfied 31 39 30 31 30 49 30
Smwht dissatisfied 36 32 39 37 35 28 39
Very di§satisfied 30 24 28 28 31 16 28
DK/NA 1 1 1 1 1
28. Do you approve or disapprove of the way Barack Obama is handling the economy?
WtBrnAgn
Tot Rep Dem Ind Men Worn Evnglcl
Approve 46% 19% 81% 33% 37% 53% 31%
Disapprove 48 79 13 56 58 40 64
DK/NA 6 2 5 11 4 8 5
Cntrl NrthE NrthW SthE SthW WstCnt
Approve 43% 49% 51% 47% 37% 45%
Disapprove 52 43 47 43 59 51
DK/NA 5 8 2 10 4 5
TREND: Do you approve or disapprove of the way Barack Obama is handling the economy?
Jul 7 May 6 Mar 18 Feb 6
2009 2009 2009 2009
Approve 46 57 53 58
Disapprove 48 36 36 21
DK/NA 6 7 11 21
Quinnipiac University • 275 Mount Carmel Ave. • Hamden, CT 06518-1908 • 203-582-8200
Stay cool with this summer's hottest movies. Moviefone brings you trailers, celebrities, movie showtimes and tickets!
Jiloty, Lauren C <JilotyLC@state.gov>
Wednesday, July 08, 2009 7:35 AM
Abedin, Huma
Mini Schedule Wednesday 7/7/09
She was flattered that her presence is missed in the building on long trips. Committed to make the building work for S
while she is traveling.
I asked if there are any long trips she's passionate about we would work it out — she said only two — if HRC ever goes to
Antarctica and Africa. I said we would work those out (her cousin is Amb to Angola so that is her real interest).
She was pleased she was impactful.
cdm
104
Happy to call. Will check in with hrc.
 
See below
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Thursday, July 09, 2009 7:29 AM
H
FYI
8:25 am PRESIDENTIAL DAILY BRIEFING
8:30 am Secretary's Office
8:30 am DAILY SMALL STAFF MEETING
8:45 am Secretary's Office
8:45 am DAILY SENIOR STAFF MEETING
9:15 am Secretary's Conference Room
9:15 am WEEKLY MEETING w/REGIONAL BUREAU SECRETARIES
10:00 am Deputy Secretary's Conference Room
10:00 am HOLD FOR HUMA
11:00 am Secretary's Office
11:00 am OFFICE TIME
12:20 pm Secretary's Office
12:20 pm DEPART State Department *En route River Entrance, Pentagon
12:30 pm ARRIVE The Pentagon
12:30 pm ONE-ON-ONE LUNCH w/DEFENSE SECRETARY ROBERT GATES
1:30 pm Secretary Gates' Private Office, Pentagon
1:35 pm DEPART The Pentagon *En route State Department
1:45 pm ARRIVE State Department
2:00 pm MEETING w/SE RICHARD HOLBROOICE
3:00 pm Secretary's Office
3:00 pm PRIVATE MEETING w/MAUREEN WHITE
3:30 pm Secretary's Office
3:30 pm OFF-THE-RECORD MEETING w/FRED HIATT AND JACKSON DIEHL,
4:00 pm WASHINGTON POST Secretary's Office
4:00 pm SCHEDULING MEETING w/LONA AND HUMA
4:30 pm Secretary's Office
4:30 pm
6:00 pm
OFFICE TIME
Secretary's Office
6:00 pm RECEPTION FOR NEW MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF
7:30 pm REPRESENTATIVES Thomas Jefferson Room, 8th Floor *Approx. 55 ppl expected.
7:30 pm (t) DEPART State Department *En route Private Residence
7:40 pm (t) ARRIVE Private Residence
###
117
July 9, 2009
For: Hillary
 
 
July 9, 2009
For: Hillary, Cheryl
 
130
Confidential fyi on traffic VI - didn't know you asked him to stay and want to know why ...
Justin:
Strobe's edits for WJC to see.
cd m
B6
Justin:
Strobe's edits for WJC to see.
cdm B6
7:30 am PHONE CALL w/SWISS FEDERAL COUNCILLOR MICHELINE
7:45 am CALMY-REY Secretary's Residence
8:15 am DEPART Private Residence *En route State Department
8:25 am ARRIVE State Department
8:25 am PRESIDENTIAL DAILY BRIEFING
8:30 am Secretary's Office
8:30 am PRIVATE BREAKFAST
9:30 am James Madison Room, 84' floor
9:30 am OFFICE TIME
10:00 am Secretary's Office
10:00 am TOWN HALL MEETING
11:00 am Dean Acheson Auditorium, First Floor *Approx. 700 employees attending.
11:30 am PHOTO OPS
11:35 am Secretary's Outer Office
12:00 pm SWEARING-IN CEREMONY FOR DANIEL BENJAMIN,
12:20 pm COORDINATOR FOR COUNTERTERRORISM Benjamin Franldin Room, 8th Floor
*Approx. 170 guests attending.
12:30 pm OFFICE TIME
1:15 pm Secretary's Office
1:15 pm MEETING w/TIM SOLSO, CEO OF CUMMINS AND CO-CHAIR US-
1:30 pm BRAZIL CEO FORUM Secretary's Office
1:30 pm BILATERAL w/EUROPEAN UNION COMMISSIONER BENITA
2:00 pm FERRERO-WALDNER Secy's Conf. Room *Camera Spray in Treaty Room preceding.
2:00 pm WEEKLY MEETING w/UN AMBASSADOR SUSAN RICE
2:30 pm Secretary's Office
2:30 pm MEETING w/DENNIS ROSS
3:00 pm Secretary's Office
3:20 pm DEPART State Department *En route Reagan National Airport
3:35 pm ARRIVE Reagan National Airport
4:00 pm DEPART Reagan National Airport via US Air Shuttle #2187
En route New York, New York-LaGuardia Airport
5:13 pm ARRIVE New York, New York
5:30 pm DEPART LaGuardia Airport
En route Private Residence
6:30 pm ARRIVE Private Residence
###
134
Dear Secretary Clinton,
I hope that your elbow is healing quickly. I mentioned that we were doing some work on maritime developments in the
region from the Persian Gulf to the East China Sea and Sea of Japan. Below are key findings from the report, but the
main takeaway is that the political impact of Chinese military modernization may be greater than a narrow technical
analysis of China's capabilities would suggest, and for a range of reasons, technical and political, prospects for regional
cooperation are limited, but pathways to conflict are numerous and increasing.
All best, Jackie
Key findings from the workshop include:
• Chinese naval modernization has proceeded at rates higher than
forecast 10 years ago and has created the capability to complicate operation of US carrier battle groups within 1,000
kilometers of the Chinese coastline.
• The Indian Ocean may in the coming decades be the operating area of
SSBNs from countries with limited experience in sustained SSBN patrols, including India, China, and possibly Pakistan.
• Chinese maritime relations with countries along the littoral area
have continued to develop, with a new friendly relationship emerging with Sri Lanka, to complement the existing
relations with Myanmar and Pakistan. This may lead to a new form of "blue-brown water" naval operations, in which
Chinese naval forces operate far from Chinese bases, but close to the coasts of client states.
The workshop tended to the conclusion that the trends in the region were not such as to make maritime cooperation
easy. These trends
include:
Japanese concern that Chinese dominance in the waters within 1,000
miles of Chinese territory has immediate consequences for Japan's maritime autonomy.
• Indian suspicion of Chinese naval developments in Hainan Island,
Chinese development of port infrastructure in Pakistan and Myanmar, and the possibility of Chinese ballistic missile
submarines operating close to India.
• Indian interest in SSBNs, plus Chinese SSBN ports in Hainan and
even, possibly, Pakistani SSBNs, all of which creates the possibility of multiple SSBN patrols in the Indian Ocean, along
with the potential for naval nuclear accidents at sea.
• Asymmetries in levels of operational competence, and technology, in
submarines and maritime aviation, which, for example, make functional multi-national naval cooperation harder for
states that are afraid of revealing technologies or weaknesses.
• The major role of land-based maritime warfare strike complexes in
this region, which means that war at sea always carries with it the risk of escalation to strikes on ground targets in
homeland areas.
The report also offers two scenarios under which the United States may consider engaging militarily in the region.
The first scenario, which concerns a clash between Japan and China in waters claimed by both, compels us to consider:
• The circumstances under which the Chinese may seek to demonstrate
that their new maritime capabilities must be taken seriously and respected, and
• What the United States would lose if it did not support the
Japanese, and then faced a world in which Japan became either a subordinate power to China or a nuclear armed state,
capable of pursuing its national interest independent of the United States.
The second scenario concerns an American naval blockade of an Iran that has tested a nuclear weapon, potentially
giving rise to an interaction between the United States and China far from the operating bases of each but close to
territory of a client of China, a "blue-brown water" clash. In this scenario, China is using its navy to show presence, and
to force the United States to ask itself whether it wants to go to war with China over a political conflict that is less than
black and white. Thinking about the options that would be left to the United States under these circumstances
underscores how Chinese naval forces may have more political impact by 2025 than a narrow assessment of their
military capabilities would suggest.
On Fri, May 22, 2009 at 7:45 AM, <newmyer wrote:
> Secretary Clinton, The Australian is the newspaper in which I read
> your remarks on Asia-Pacific. Thank you again, Jackie
> Sent from my Verizon Wireless BlackBerry
>
Below is the statement of very impressive Palau reps at the end of a session of required meetings on the next
phase of free association aid. FYI only, the Palauans were insulted by the nature and depth of the response to
their proposal as well as the content and the overall approach. They are even privately questioning the
relationship. (This hasn't affected their intent to take the Uighurs.) I will send a few further thoughts.
At the conclusion of yesterday's meeting, the Palau delegation caucused to discuss its reaction to the response of the United
States delegation to the proposals that it made in June in Washington D.C., and expanded upon in subsequent communications.
While the Palau delegation has agreed to respond to certain additional questions raised by the United States delegation on specific
elements of the Palau proposal, and further has agreed to participate in certain working groups on specific issues, the Palau
delegation was deeply disappointed with the response of the United States delegation. The United States delegation did not
seriously respond, as required by the Compact, to the operational requirements of the Government of Palau or to Palau's
comprehensive and considered plans to achieve economic advancement and self-sufficiency.
In light of the foregoing, the Palau delegation has determined that it must now return to Palau to discuss with President Toribiong
the next steps that Palau needs to take regarding the Compact. Thank you.
Jeff
Jeffrey L. Farrow
202-343-2905 o
Attached is the latest version of the speech, incorporating comments from Sandy and Strobe, as well as edits from
Cheryl and Anne-Marie and Lissa.
While it has improved, it has also grown in length. It is now just a bit shorter than your Senate confirmation
testimony. There are places to cut, but I want you to see it in full so you can make your own assessments.
John Podesta will send a few additional thoughts later today or tomorrow — the rest of his comments are captured in
this revised text.
Dennis is going to sharpen and hone the sections on the Middle East and Iran, and I will ask Holbrooke to work on the
Af-Pak piece.
I am available any time to discuss.
142
Read through - nice complement to jose's induction to the process
We can leave then for now - we can work around as nee be and they have a few connections to companies we don't.
Asked philippe for a plan - he may want to sole source it to get the coverage but if not, yes.
Cdm
Fyi
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Saturday, July 11, 2009 7:48 AM
Fw: Congratulations!
See b/I
 
I have his email B6
May have his cell too- ill check my files
His cell is
B6
Jones wants to talk to you
He's wheels up from ghana at 2:30.
Wants to follow up post carter call.
1 SS
They said:"Our side has been dialing on Friday evening and Saturday morning our time (Saturday morning and Saturday
evening over there), with no answer. Our side will keep trying, starting again this evening (Sunday morning over there).
1s6
Kurt is CampbelIKM@state.gov
I'm working on donilon
Jiloty, Lauren C <JilotyLC@state.gov>
Saturday, July 11, 2009 6:28 PM
Re: N. Korea
Tom donilon
Campbell, Kurt M <CampbelIKM@state.gov>
Saturday, July 11, 2009 9:43 PM
Re: N. Korea
Secretary Clinton -
 
Had a good call yesterday with our team, reaching out to treasury on change and should know more today.
4cr
Where are you on it - will you have a revised version today to give direction of your desires?
At moment we have addl comments in from a derek, sandy, george (on mep), dennis r, ams and we are holding off
doing a new draft until we get a sense from you about your edits.
Cdm
167
Fyi
169
Sending now - their will be a series of emails
Per your request — here are AMS' comments in text and general below.
Oscar should print for you so you can see the red-line as it will not show up on your bb.
cdm
Derek's comments — again in redline in text so Oscar should print so you can see them.
cdm
Dennis comments below and but primarily in text in track changes.
cdm
Jim's comments on the same draft — also in track changes in text.
cdm
Below are PJ's comments/edits in this email (i.e., no attachment).
All of Sandy's were incorporated in the draft you have except his point
that: "Finally, there needs to be a key para that sets forth the lens through which through which you want the speech to
be seen."
We actually are still awaiting George's comments on ME para.
cdm
Secretary,
Garten, David (Lautenberg) <David_Garten@lautenberg.senate.gov>
Sunday, July 12, 2009 4:23 PM
H2
Small World
I wanted to let you know that last night I met old friends of yours and your husband's —
Best,
David
173
You'll be happy to know that Jack and I have been working this weekend on behalf of our good friends in Palau. They
will be getting new numbers in the next round of negotiations. I will stay on top of it, though no matter what I don't
think they will be 100 percent satisfied.
Sullivan, Jacob _I <SullivanJJ@state.gov>
Sunday, July 12, 2009 7:17 PM
H; cheryl.mills
Re: Speech
I literally just got off the phone with Jim Steinberg. He will have specific comments tomorrow, but his overall comment
was that t
(Apologies for any lack of clarity in how I relay these points -- I'm writing on blackberry and our conversation was brief.)
 
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Monday, July 13, 2009 8:40 PM
Oscar will be late tonite, won't get to dc till midnight fyi.
0
lRfl
Muscatine Lissa
Tuesday, July 14, 2009 5:33 AM
CFR draft
The draft still needs a lot of work.
Will do.
On Jul 14, 2009, at 5:35 AM, H wrote:
> Thanks so much. Pls send it to me at same time so I can review as
> well.
>
Ok
Muscatine Lissa
Tuesday, July 14, 2009 7:43 AM
H
Huma Abedin; Lissa Muscatine
CFR latest draft
CFR for HRC 7.14.09 730 am.dat; ATT00001.txt
This is getting there.
Yes
Lissa Muscatine
Tuesday, July 14, 2009 9:57 AM
Re: CFR latest draft
On Tue, Jul 14, 2009 at 9:46 AM, H <HDR22@clintonemai1.com> wrote:
It is getting better. I've gone thru it once and will be ready to discuss later. Thank you s000 much.
I emailed it to you a few minutes ago. Do you want me to fax it as well?
Faxing to you now.
You should have received two faxes stacked together accidentally. The one you want says "9 pm" on the top left. I am
sending the remaining pages (about 5-6) now. The one that says 8:15 pm is the wrong version so ignore it.
• 212
9:45 am DEPART Private Residence *En route White House
9:55 am ARRIVE White House
10:00 am PRESIDENT'S EXPANDED BILATERAL w/DUTCH PRIME MINISTER
10:30 am JAN PETER BALICENENDE White House Oval Office
10:30 am PRESIDENT'S STATEMENT TO THE PRESS w/ PM BALKENEDE
10:45 am White House Oval Office
10:50 am DEPART White House *En route State Department
10:55 am ARRIVE State Department
11:00 am OFFICE TIME
2:00 pm Secretary's Office
2:00 pm MEETING w/UNDER SECRETARY ELLEN TAUSCHER
2:30 pm Secretary's Office
2:45 pm BILATERAL w/DUTCH FOREIGN MINISTER MAXIME 'VERHAGEN
3:15 pm Secretary's Conference Room *Camera spray in Treaty Room preceding.
3:30 pm PHOTO OPS (3)
4:00 pm Secretary's Outer Office and Marshall Room
4:00 pm BILATERAL w/LATVIAN FOREIGN MINISTER MARIS RIEKSTINS
4:30 pm Secretary's Conference Room *Camera spray in Treaty Room preceding.
4:30 pm PC PRE-BRIEF MEETING
4:45 pm Secretary's Office
4:45 pm (t) PHONE CALL w/BRITISH FS DAVID MILIBAND
5:05 pm (t) Secretary's Office
5:10 pm DEPART State Department *En route White House
5:15 pm ARRIVE White House
5:15 pm WEEICLY PC MEETING
6:30 pm White House Situation Room
6:35 pm DEPART White House *En route Private Residence
6:50 pm ARRIVE Private Residence
FYI:
9:15 am POTUS PRE-BRIEF MEETING
Oval Office
9:30 am POTUS ONE-ON-ONE w/DUTCH PM BALDENEDE
10:00am Oval Office
###
•
-2014-20439 Doc No. C05763077 Date: 06/30/2015
done
FYI
See below
In the good news department...
Good. Just incorporating some line edits from Cheryl and want to make sure I got all of yours in. Have been getting
feedback from Podesta et. al. Will have new draft to you shortly.
Will do.
You will have a tight draft in 30 minutes — at 8:15-ish..
202
I will send latest to them. WH has reviewed too.
Sorry about the gaps and typos. Will clean it up. And of course we can chat whenever you're ready.
Sure. Will send as soon as I can.
Will do
I hope I got all the gaps/typos. Will send to WJC now.
208
 
Do you want me just to drive it over to you? I could be there in 10 minutes.
8:05 am ARRIVE State Department
8:05 am BREAKFAST w/CONGRESSIONAL BLACK CAUCUS MEMBERS
9:15 am Thomas Jefferson Room, 8th Floor
9:30 am BIWEEKLY MEETING w/MANAGEMENT TEAM
10:00 am Deputy Secretary's Conference Room
10:10 am DEPART State Department *En route White House
10:15 am ARRIVE White House
10:15 am WEEKLY MEETING w/ SECRETARY GATES AND GENERAL JONES
10:45 am White House Situation Room
10:50 am SMALL GROUP MEETING
12:15 pm White House Situation Room
12:30 pm DEPART White House *En route Council on Foreign Relations
12:35 pm ARRIVE Council on Foreign Relations
12:40 pm SPEECH TO THE COUNCIL ON FOREIGN RELATIONS
2:00 pm Council on Foreign Relations
2:05 pm DEPART Council on Foreign Relations *En route State Department
2:15 pm ARRIVE State Department
2:45 pm MEETING w/BERTIE AHERN, BOARD MEMBER, CO-OPERATION
3:15 pm IRELAND AND FORMER PRIME MINISTER OF IRELAND
214
Secretary's Office
3:30 pm BILATERAL w/CHADIAN FOREIGN MINISTER MOUSSA FAKI
4:00 pm Secretary's Conference Room *Camera spray in Treaty Room preceding.
4:25 pm DEPART State Department *En route White House
4:30 pm ARRIVE White House
4:30 pm WEEKLY MEETING w/PRESIDENT OBAMA AND VP BIDEN
5:00 pm Oval Office
5:00 pm DEPART White House *En route State Department
5:05 pm ARRIVE State Department
5:15 pm OFFICE TIME
6:00 pm Secretary's Office
6:00 pm DEPART State Department *En route Private Residence
6:10 pm ARRIVE Private Residence ###
715
Jim K. sent in some edits in the middle of the night -- strictly designed to trim/improve flow. Think it's worth you flipping
through to see if any strike you as worth making.
Jack is going to chair the meeting and knows to start if you aren't there in time or can't make it altogether. Yes, Sarah F
knows you are coming closer to 10:30am.
Will do.
Sullivan, Jacob J <Sullivanii@state.gov>
Wednesday, July 15, 2009 7:44 AM
Re: FW: 8:30 draft
Fyi
Fyi
Can you all advise— what are we doing on this.
Jack had Mike made you aware of this?
cdm
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Wednesday, July 15, 2009 1:44 PM
Re: Art
Will be off campus at meeting
But you should definately come, I think they have found some good things.
fvi
241
Many thanks for all you help and attention to her speech today. So valuable and so appreciative.
Best.
cdm
242
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Thursday, July 16, 2009 12:04 AM
Strobe Talbott
Speech
Strobe
Just wanted to say many thanks for all your help on the Secretary speech. Your guidance was invaluable and it will only
earn you more work.
Xo
cdm
243
See b/I
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Thursday, July 16, 2009 7:04 AM
Sullivan, Jacob J
Fw: Speech
Strobe Talbott <
Thursday, July 16, 2009 7:26 AM
RE: THANK YOU!
Thanks, Hillary. the speech turned out very, very well. Devin represented the family and sent me a rave review a while
back. I missed the plug for the book, but I thank you for that. More important, I'm glad it was of some use as you
prepare for a very important trip. I'll send you later an op-ed I'm working on about the climate/nonpro agenda with
India, pegged to your trip. Safe travels, and thanks again for letting me kibitz on your good works. S.
This is getting there.
8:25 am PFtESIDENTIAL DAILY BRIEFING
8:30 am Secretary's Office
8:30 am DAILY SMALL STAFF MEETING
8:45 am Secretary's Office
8:45 am DAILY SENIOR STAFF MEETING
9:15 am Secretary's Conference Room
9:15 am WEEKLY MEETING w/REGIONAL BUREAU SECRETARIES
10:00 am Deputy Secretary's Conference Room
10:15am PRE-BRIEF ON AFTERNOON PRESS INTERVIEWS
10:30am Secretary's Office
10:40 am MEET AND GREET w/CANADIAN FM LAWRENCE CANNON
10:45 am AND MEXICAN FS PATRICIA ESPINOSA *Official photo at top.
10:45 am NORTH AMERICAN TRILATERAL MINISTERIAL
12:00 pm Benjamin Franklin Room, 8°' Floor '"Camera Spray preceding.
12:10 pm NORTH AMERICAN TRILATERAL WORKING LUNCH
1:00 pm James Monroe Room, 8th Floor
1:00 pm TRILATERAL PRESS PRE-BRIEF MEETING
1:15 pm Secretary's Office
1:15 pm TRILATERAL PRESS AVAILABILITY w/CANADIAN FM
1:45 pm CANNON AND MEXICAN FS PATRICIA ESPINOSA
Benjamin Franklin Room, 8" Floor
2:15 pm PRIVATE MEETING (Danny Abraham)
2:30 pm Secretary's Office
2:30pm PHOTO w/US AMB TO VENEZUELA PATRICK DUDDY
2:35pm Secretary's Office
2:45 pm TAPED TELEVISION INTERVIEW VIA SATELLITE w/RAJDEEP
2:55 pm SARDESAI, CNN lB Press Studio, 211° Floor
3:00 pm INTERVIEW w/ANWAR IQBAL, DAWN TELEVISION (T)
3:10 pm Press Studio, 2°° Floor
3:15pm 0Th PULL ASIDE w/LAURA ROZEN
3:20pm Location: TBD, Staff: Philippe
3:30 pm BILATERAL w/IRAQI FOREIGN MINISTER HOSHYAR ZEBARI
4:00 pm Secretary's Conference Room *Camera Spray in Treaty Room preceding.
4:15 pm PHONE CALL w/FS DAVID MILIBAND
4:30 pm Secretary's Office
4:50 pm DEPART State Department
En route Andrews AFB
5:20 pm ARRIVE Andrews AFB
5:30 pm DEPART Andrews Air Force Base via Air Force Aircraft Tail #80002
En route Prague, Czech Republic ###
740
Always glad to pitch in. It came out great and your delivery was fantastic! Onward and upward!
Jiloty, Lauren C <JilotyLC@state.gov>
Thursday, July 16, 2009 9:02 AM
H; BStrider
RE: Tony Campolo... Fw: Your help is needed
Hi Burns! I'll forward you the most up-to-date information.
Thank you for your kind words -- it's an honor to work for you. In the words of some wise person I heard recently, now
we have to deliver.
Thanks so much. Safe travels in India and Thailand. I'll be getting the China S+ED ready!
HRC: Back this morning from Asia.
Congratulations on the speech. I think it came out great. And the reaction I have heard today has been very
positive.
Let raise an idea about how you could present the arrangement on settlements that you are seeking with Israel as
I understand it, i.e. a moratorium coupled with allowances to complete a number of housing units. There are
two ways:
1. To describe it as an agreement, explaining why the US has accepted an Israeli completion of a
handful of units whose construction already has begun. This raises some concerns. It would
represent U.S. legitimization of some (however small) Israeli activity in the West Bank and it
would trigger Arab and Palestinian complaints that we had compromised, sowing doubts about
our effectiveness.
2. The alternative would be for the administration to say:
a. We have come a very long way, as Israel has made unprecedented commitments to the U.S. in terms of a
settlements freeze. This is a very welcome development.
b. We did not achieve all that we had hoped as Israel intends to complete a number of
housing units. We have differences with the Israeli government on this matter which we
have expressed to them..
•c. That said, we are convinced that substantial progress has been made that warrants
an immediate resumption of peace talks as well as Arab steps toward Israel that will help
promote a two-state solution.
This latter option retains our credibility, does not compromise our oft-stated position and allows us to move
forward.
Of course, I am around if you want to discuss.
Good luck in India. They are very excited about your visit.
Sandy
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Friday, July 17, 2009 12:57 PM
H
FW: sister-in-law
fyi
Fyi
fyi
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Friday, July 17, 2009 10:45 PM
FW: from today's Financial Times....
Not sure - we have seeking to do so with Jack who is working on it
I'll call him this week. I think we have this largely sorted.
Jeff and I go back to Puerto Rico and Guam in the primaries.
just seeing — am up and on line — will also try calling you when looks like down time on your calendar
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Sunday, July 19, 2009 12:05 PM
H
1.4(B)
1.4(D)
B1
Please pass to S:
07/19/2019
17n
Below is Palau's statement on the recent meeting in the required free association review. The fourth is the key
paragraph. Jake, I'll call. Jeff 202-343-2905 o,
A Compact of Free Association replaced the United States administration of Palau, islands which the U.S. took in war and
subsequently administered for the United Nations. The Compact, which was signed in 1986 and took effect October 1,
1994, includes provisions of various duration. Some are to last at least 50 years, including full U.S. military authority --
although the power of the U.S. to deny access to Palau and its extensive waters by the military of any other nation is to
continue in perpetuity.
The amounts and types of U.S. budgetary and programmatic assistance to Palau under the Compact are specified for 15
years, but the Compact requires reviews of its terms and the entire relationship on its 15th, 30th, and
40th anniversaries. The reviews are to consider the operating requirements of the Government of Palau and the islands'
development. The Compact also commits the U.S. to acting on the findings and to promoting Palau's long-term economic
development.
A Palauan delegation that included Vice President Kerai Mariur, Chief Representative for Compact Review Joshua
Koshiba, Minister of Health Dr. Stevenson J. Kuartei, Palau Community College President Dr. Patrick Tellei, Ambassador
to the U.S. Hersey Kyota, Representative to the United Nations Stuart Beck, and their consultants met in Honolulu on July
8-9 in connection with the 15th Anniversary Review with an American delegation that included Department of State Office
of Australia, New Zealand, and Pacific Islands Affairs Alcy Frelick, the head of the US Delegation, and representatives of
the Departments of the Interior and Defense and the Weather and Postal Services.
The U.S. delegation made positive statements on a few matters and agreed to discuss some others further. A number of
the U.S. delegation's statements, however, evidenced a need for greater study by some U.S. officials of the intent as well
as the letter of the Compact, the relationship as a whole, Palau's economic situation and fiscal responsibility
commitments, and Palau's contributions to the U.S. and to international harmony -- including sacrifice by Palauans in the
U.S. military, the UN international peacekeeping force and Palau's strategic location and posture, and Palau's positions in
the U.N.
Palau is grateful for its partnership with the U.S. and wants to continue in the association as called for by the Compact,
deepen the relationship, and develop its capacities as a freely associated state. It appreciates the more positive
expressions of U.S. Secretaries of State Clinton and of the Interior Salazar and congressional leaders of both political
parties. Palau fully trusts that reflection will result in an approach to the relationship consistent with the Compact and to
positions befitting the great nation that is the United States.
Recognizing that the questions of the association are relatively small and unique for the Government of the U.S. and that
the U.S. faces many and extraordinary challenges at this time, Palau understands why more deliberation by U.S. officials
can be needed.
Because of this, because of the confidence that it has in the United States, and because it would not be productive to
elaborate with others on the conversations at this stage, Palau's representatives are confining additional comment to
official communications.
B6
FYI
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Tuesday, July 21, 2009 3:28 PM
Sullivan, Jacob J; Abedin, Huma; H
FW: Goma
Per our conversation
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Tuesday, July 21, 2009 5:37 PM
H
FW: Ex-U.S. Diplomat Talks With Hamas
Remind me to discuss this with you.
 
Hillary, having followed your India visit closely—and, of course, the follow-up coverage on
issues you covered there—I've got a couple of thoughts, one in particular re India-Pakistan, that
I'd like to discuss with you at your convenience (if there is such a thing) in August. I'll be back
in DC from Aspen on August 7 and here through Labor Day if there's any chance of
connecting. Strobe
Strobe Talbott
President, The Brookings Institution
1775 Massachusetts Avenue NW
Washington, DC 20036
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Wednesday, July 22, 2009 12:47 PM
Sullivan, Jacob J; H
Fw:
I can dO a meeting on Saturday am if that works or Sunday am. Which is better for you?
Sullivan, Jacob J <SullivanJJ@state.gov>
Friday, July 24, 2009 4:51 AM
H
Steinberg memo
I spoke with both Kurt and Jeff about Jim's paper on Dai, which Huma has. Both were very impressed but had a number
of substantive thoughts.
They would cast the point in a different way,
which they are thinking through.
Kurt says that he will talk to Jim and then perhaps provide his own thoughts in a paper to you.
Meanwhile, I have asked Derek to do something resembling "debate on a page," to distill the key points and objectives
into a single short document that can serve as a cribsheet and help you avoid the crushing burden of the paper in the
binder.
We are prepared to keep refining and improving the paper thru the weekend.
21111
281
Are you fine with that?
cdm
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Friday, July 24, 2009 5:43 PM
H
Title Issue
286
Let me know if today or tomorrow works for you (or if you would rather find time monday).
I have a dinner at 5pm I have to get my house ready for so my best times are 13/f 2pm today or anytime tomorrow.
Cdm
290
291
didn't call me back yesterday.
Will call her again today.
s fine for wednesday visit.
Great
Also, jim Jones just called for you. Can be non-secure
°
70S
Jim just called me.
Angela has some thing you need to see before tomorrow that she cannot leave.
She's scheduled to be there at 10.
Marina knows.
296
Philippe got final edits
You will have no later than 11:30
You probably already know this, but I just heard from a friend who is wired at Meet the Press that David Gregory will ask
you about David Maziar, the Newsweek journalist arrested in Iran.
Huma said she's getting to you now
It's laid out on the first page, but we're doing two calls
1pm: call w/Axelrod, Gibbs, Denis and Nancy Deparle to brf you (their request)
1:45 call/us, plus Denis
I'll MC both and make sure you know exactly who is on
Ops will connect you to both
Report: North Korea willing to hold talks with US AP
By KWANG-TAE KIM
Associated Press
Sat Jul 25, 4:51 am ET
SEOUL, South Korea — North Korea has indicated its interest in holding direct talks with the United States, a news report
said, after the two sides traded barbs over Pyongyang's nuclear weapons programs at a security forum. "We are not
against a dialogue. We are not against any negotiation for the issues of common concern," Japan's Kyodo news agency
quoted North Korean ambassador to the United Nations Sin Son Ho as saying Friday. But the ambassador, speaking in
New York, dismissed the possibility of a return to stalled nuclear negotiations involving the two Koreas, the U.S., Japan,
China and Russia, saying "the six-party talks are gone forever." The U.S. has offered to hold talks with the North within
the six-nation process if it returns to the negotiating table and takes irreversible steps for denuclearization. Last
weekend, Assistant U.S. Secretary of State Kurt Campbell indicated that the chances for direct talks between North
Korea and the U.S. were slim. "Our bilateral negotiations are between the U.S. and South Korea about our collective
approach" to the North, Campbell told reporters in Seoul. Sin said the five other parties to the nuclear talks "cheated"
North Korea, accusing them of not implementing what they had agreed under a disarmament-for-aid deal. No more
details were given in the Kyodo report. Sin was not available for comment Saturday. The North Korean mission to the
U.N. declined to comment. North Korea quit the nuclear talks in April to protest a U.N. statement condemning a rocket
launch. North Korea insisted it sent a satellite into orbit, while the U.S. and its allies said it was actually a long-range
missile test. North Korea conducted its second nuclear test in May and a barrage of missile tests in July, drawing
international condemnation and new U.N. sanctions. U.S. and Chinese officials are expected to discuss North Korea's
nuclear programs and other regional security issues at a strategic dialogue next week in Washington. "North Korea will
be a significant topic, but obviously one among many," State Department spokesman Philip Crowley said Friday in
Washington. The U.S. and North Korea engaged in a sharp war of words earlier this week over U.S. Secretary of State
Hillary Rodham Clinton's recent comment likening the regime in Pyongyang to "small children" demanding attention. At
a regional security conference in Thailand, Clinton also said the North "has no friends left." North Korea's Foreign
Ministry described her Thursday as "a funny lady" who sometimes "looks like a primary schoolgirl and sometimes a
pensioner going shopping."
298
Yes
No word back from kristy but I told her 7am Karine and barbara will be there at 7:15.
Call reminders: holbrooke and moratinos.
79Q
Tom shannon passed on the below points:
The Honduran Armed Forces released a statement late last evening. It makes the following points:
- The Armed Forces respect the Constitution and the laws and reaffirms its subordination to civil authority in conformity
with law and obedience.
- As an institution, the Armed Forces backs a solution to the crisis Honduras faces through a process of negotiation in
the framework of the San Jose Accords.
- Accordingly, we reiterate our unrestricted support for the results of the same, in accordance with the Constitution and
laws.
- The Armed Forces as an institution will continue to fulfill the missions given it to it by the Constitutions and the laws of
Honduras.
I do
It's h
Kristy out of town.
Karine and barbara at 715
1n1
; Huma Abedin B6
I'm checking with Pat on the 50k, will work with Jack & Jake on rest.
Also, Huma has for you a follow up memo from the prep call
302
I will actually meet you at your house, I have the answers to most of your questions from last night
And will include the 5 points
o Is the 50k figure State and AID?
YES [U/S Kennedy & Ops]
o Re Sudan: how do you pronounce Abyei? What is % and dollar increase in
2010 budget for ops and aid?
Per the VoA pronunciation guide: ab-YAY (Ops). The FY09 base level for Sudan assistance programs is $327m vs $403m
in FY10- mostly related to infrastructure and election/referendum requirements. This does NOT include several hundred
million dollars of food aid and other humanitarian assistance that is also provided yearly (close to $400m on top of
numbers
below) a year. Also in addition is funding for UN peacekeeping missions- also nearly $200m a year [D(L)]
o I don't understand the answer to the prostitution policy question. What's the simplest way to say it?
[Per D(L): Because of the politics of health care reform on the Hill, there is great sensitivity about addressing the
substance of these issues at this time.]
Q: Under the previous Administration organizatioris receiving HIV\AIDs funds from the U.S. Government were required
to have a policy explicitly opposing prostitution and sex trafficking. Is that going to continue to be the policy of this
Administration?
A: This matter has been the subject of litigation - outside groups have sued both USAID and the HHS over the policy -
and we recently notified the Court that we needed additional time to review the policy. That review is underway; no
final decisions have been made.
On 7/25/09 8:46 PM, "Evergreen" <Hdr22@clintonemail.com> wrote:
> Is the 50k figure State and AID?
> Kurdistan election results?
> Can you find out for me how many Nazi prison camps we had in US during
> WW2 and what we did w the detainees--did we ever try any? Did we
> deport them after war ended?
> Re Sudan: how do you pronounce Abyei?
> What is % and dollar increase in 2010 budget for ops and aid?
>
> I don't understand the answer to the prostitution policy question.
> What's the simplest way to say it?
Oof, sorry
Yes
Thanks!
306
Fyi
Madame Secretary-
A first rate job on Meet the Press. Your experience, your skill, your competency and humor all on strong display.
Wendy
Wendy R. Sherman
Albright Stonebridge Group*
1101 New York Avenue, NW
Suite 900
Washin ton DC 20005
Tel:
Fax
* On June 25, 2009, Stonebridge International and The Albright Group announced their merger, creating the Albright Stonebridge
Group. For the time being, all contact information remains the same. Once we complete the transition, we will inform you of our new
contact details. We appreciate your patience and look forward to continuing our work with you.
sent from Blackberry
B6
You did a really fine job on Meet the Press today. The Russia, Iran, Afghanistan and Asia points were all right
on the mark. And even though it goes beyond my professional scope, the second half was just as good. Enjoy
the rest of the weekend.
Bill Classified by DAS, A/GIS, DoS on 06/30/2015 — Class:
07/25/2024
Madam Secretary--Really terrific work this morning. Great appearance.
Best.
Tom
308
Fyi
Great job this morning. Glad it went well.
Hope you get a few hours off this afternoon -- though I assume that with the China prep not likely.
On Sat, Jul 25, 2009 at 8:46 PM, H <HDR22@clintonemail.com> wrote:
Is the 50k figure State and AID?
Kurdistan election results?
Can you find out for me how many Nazi prison camps we had in US during WW2 and what we did w the
detainees--did we ever try any? Did we deport them after war ended?
Re Sudan: how do you pronounce Abyei?
What is % and dollar increase in 2010 budget for ops and aid?
I don't understand the answer to the prostitution policy question. What's the simplest way to say it?
Fabulous. Couldn't have been better
Abedin, Huma <AbedinH@state.gov>
Sunday, July 26, 2009 12:21 PM
H
Fw: for HRC
Whenever you do something big on TV we all hear from lots of folks saying you did great. But this time is noticeably
different. First, people across the spectrum - DC insiders, reporters, staff, ex-staff, friends of friends, WH folks, etc -
were blown away. Second, people were REALLY moved by the last segment, three people even told me they teared up.
I'm guessing and hoping you hear this directly from random folks in the coming days.
And I think because it's been a lousy couple of weeks for the Admin, with mixed messages and bad news, coupled with
many people seeing you for the first time for an extended period talking about the job and your relationship with the
President, and that combo was probably the most powerful reminder since your speech in Denver that you're in a class
all your own (including the President who became enmeshed in the Gates incident)
That you didn't wait for the envoy question was key, you turned it into a strength. What you said about the President
and how you said it, one can't help but think how much of a team player you are and how remarkably you've adapted to
the role.
You were definitely on your game. You either threw a perfect game - or at least a no hitter. So this couldn't have gone
better, achieved everything we needed to times 10, and comes on the heels of a great 10 days.
Will be interesting to see the storyline that emanates from this. Because there was no substantive news, it'll be a focus
on style especially saving Biden.
Fyi
Fyi
RELEASE IN PART B5,B6
You were terrific on MTP. You'll be either happy -- or horrified -- to know that
conducted in front of the tv so the clan could watch.
A short while ago, Kurt sent me the below thoughts on your private conversation with Dai:
was largely B6
B5
Sorry I missed you last night —
Issues:
Personnel
Other Issues:
Support Needs for Dialogs
Monthly Thinking Group — Politically/Positionally -- [Sandy Berger, Vartan Gregorian, John Podesta, Jim
Kennedy, Minyon Moore, Strobe Talbott, Maggie Williams,]
Agenda — what do you want to claim — non-pro; development reform; NK?
Education Initiative:
• Dinner on 18 August
• Goal would be to begin implementing strategy of getting thinking per JS memo: the role higher education is and
can play as part of "smart diplomacy", including development to enhance the network or relationships between
countries and peoples to elevate the conditions and capacities of peoples around the world.
• Potential guest list:
Text of attachment below:
To: Cheryl Mills, COS
 
Holbrooke in brussels. Asking to talk to u at 8am today.
324
Mills, Cheryl D <MillsCD@state.gov>
Tuesday, July 28, 2009 9:22 PM
H
FW: Secretary of State's visit to Africa
FYI
Holbrooke asking to talk sometime this am.
Isabelle 715
329
Fyi
Yes, we will send a message first thing.
I'm checking and will get right back to you.
DCA negotiations are still on for week after next (11-13 Aug), as requested.
Amb Barco called to request that we slide right one day (13,14 Aug). They requested this based on a visit of Mexican
President Calderon - who will visit Bogota (10-12 Aug). The dep FM and some MinDef officials want to be in Bogota for
Calderon's visit.
Let me know if you have any other questions.
pvervee
Secretary Clinton —
I understand you are going to Kenya next week and while I know the trip is primarily focused on trade issues, I
wanted to flag an issue for you because I know it is near and dear to your heart.
Kenya has one of the strictest anti-abortion laws in Africa — it is illegal unless a woman's life is at risk and
criminalizes both the woman and the provider. Two years ago, Kenyan authorities imprisoned a doctor and
two nurses, falsely accusing them of providing illegal abortions. After a year in prison, the providers were
found innocent and released, but it galvanized the legal and provider community who formed a coalition to
make abortion less restrictive. It will come as no surprise to you that, as a result of their abortion law, Kenya
has one of the highest maternal mortality rates in all of Africa, with an estimated 800 women a day seeking
the procedure, often through dangerous means.
Kenya is restarting a long-stalled constitutional review process and they hope to produce a final Constitution
by next year. Religious groups are on a concerted crusade to include new language in the Constitution which
would codify that "life begins at conception". The current Constitution is largely silent on the issue. If this fetal
personhood amendment goes forward, it would place Kenya in the small community of nations with such a
provision. It would clearly mark Kenya as out of stop with countries attempting to institutionalize the African
Union's Maputo Protocol, one of the most progressive regional documents on women, development and
reproductive rights, and with the vast majority of African countries in general. For a country trying to regain
the momentum of stability and success it enjoyed until recently, such a policy imposition would be a
regression for women's rights and for the country writ large.
I went to Kenya last month to work with the coalition that has formed to strategize against the Constitutional
amendment and to work toward a less restrictive abortion law. I also visited several of our clinics and
providers in Nairobi and in nearby villages where Planned Parenthood has programs to train providers in post
abortion care. You have seen this a million times in your travels around the world, so I don't need to tell you
how poignant the stories were of the lives saved and lost, the bravery in standing up to constant government
harassment, and the fear of what this potential Constitutional amendment will mean to the provision of safe
medical services. I know it is asking a lot, but if there is any way that you could draw attention to this issue
when you are in Kenya, you would be even more of my personal hero than you already are. It is our hope that
if Kenya knows the world is watching they may be more careful in how they proceed. Of course we would be
happy to help you in any way if you decide you want to do something on this while you are there. There is also
a Congressional delegation going to Kenya the week of August 8th and we are working on them to have a side
meeting on this issue as well.
As always, thank you so much for all you do. We are all so grateful that you are there! All best, Laurie
Laurie Rubiner
Vice President of Public Policy and Advocacy
Planned Parenthood Federation of America
(202) 973-4863 office
She is on your grid. Rob will take care of the letter right away.
I am traveling and will be out of the office from Friday, July 31- Wednesday, August 5. I will check emails when possible. If you
need assistance, please contact Anne Fauvre at 202-842-7222 or Thank You.
Laurie — She isn't doing any specific health or womens events in Kenya but I've also shared your email with policy team
at state and embassy staff in Nairobi helping to plan the trip to see if there is any way to address this.
I'm on my way to your house to drop off:
- schedule for tomorrow. Marianne at 630am. Isabelle at 8am. Catherine coming monday.
- also dropped off some work folders which includes africa info.
- jim steinberg wants to talk tonite. Doesn't need to be secure.
- its 13 people coming tomorrow, I've worked it out with marina and doug
350
